<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
<title type="text">Nicola du Toit</title>
<generator uri="https://github.com/mojombo/jekyll">Jekyll</generator>
<link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://nicoladutoit.com/feed.xml" />
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://nicoladutoit.com" />
<updated>2015-02-04T14:57:20+02:00</updated>
<id>http://nicoladutoit.com/</id>
<author>
  <name>Nicola du Toit</name>
  <uri>http://nicoladutoit.com/</uri>
  <email>nicoladutoit@gmail.com</email>
</author>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[So you need a website...]]></title>
  <link>http://nicoladutoit.com/articles/so-you-need-a-website</link>
  <id>http://nicoladutoit.com/articles/so-you-need-a-website</id>
  <updated>2015-02-04T00:00:00-00:00</updated>
  <published>2015-02-04T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  
  <author>
    <name>Nicola du Toit</name>
    <uri>http://nicoladutoit.com</uri>
    <email>nicoladutoit@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s been an appallingly long time since I blogged. Almost a year. 2014 included finishing a Masters degree in IT and changing jobs amongst other things. Writing fell by the wayside. So there. Life happens. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moving swiftly onwards into the new year - I&#39;ve recently been asked by several friends for advice on setting up a website. Their needs range from simple blogs to professional sites for work. What surprised me was how much they seemed to think I may know about the weird and wonderful realm of the Internet. And then I remembered that building websites has become one of those things that feels really normal to me but is closer to black magic for most folks. What follows is a quick and (hopefully) handy guide on how to get started with a website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;1. Decide on your budget&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Knowing how much money you&#39;re willing to fork out for your new site is important. Would you gladly spend ZAR50 000 getting a fancy, customised site built? In this case proceed straight to a serious design agency or web developer and get the job done by a pro. If your budget is more like R200 then the best option is probably to rent your own domain and go with free hosting (more about this later).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;2. Choosing a domain&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
What is a domain name? http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Domain_name

One does not simply choose a domain name. Your domain name can say a lot about your website and your brand. Firstly, it must be easy to remember. www.thisismyawesomewebsiteitssocool.org.za is great example of what not to call your site. Secondly, it must be unambiguous to read, unlike expertsexchange.net or masterbaitonline.com. (For more entertaining fails have a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.boredpanda.com/worst-domain-names/&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;read here). Thirdly, believe it or not, domain suffixes actually have &lt;i&gt;meaning&lt;/i&gt;. Don&#39;t call your site projectmanager.xxx unless your really &lt;i&gt;really&lt;/i&gt; mean it. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.computerhope.com/jargon/num/domains.htm&quot;&gt;Here&#39;s a helpful list&lt;/a&gt; of domain suffixes and their meanings. If you&#39;re happy with a generic domain name like mysite.blogspot.com....&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;To host or not to host&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;hosting. - what is it, options. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Easy
Blogger - Google. Free. No hosting. 
Wordpress.com for free. can register domain through them or customise with your own. http://en.support.wordpress.com/domains/. Free themes.
No hosting
Wix.com&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Medium
Wordpress.org - more advanced. FTP access. Free themes. NEed hosting&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hard
Jekyll. Free themes. Need to know Github. Need hosting. (can use git domain)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;L33t
HTML + CSS, boostrap or similar. Need domain and hosting.&lt;/p&gt;


  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://nicoladutoit.com/articles/so-you-need-a-website&quot;&gt;So you need a website...&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Nicola du Toit at &lt;a href=&quot;http://nicoladutoit.com&quot;&gt;Nicola du Toit&lt;/a&gt; on February 04, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[On cooking hake]]></title>
  <link>http://nicoladutoit.com/articles/on-cooking-hake</link>
  <id>http://nicoladutoit.com/articles/on-cooking-hake</id>
  <updated>2014-03-17T00:00:00-00:00</updated>
  <published>2014-03-17T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  
  <author>
    <name>Nicola du Toit</name>
    <uri>http://nicoladutoit.com</uri>
    <email>nicoladutoit@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve never been a huge fan of seafood. When I was a wee lass my favourite thing in the world was fish paste on toast, but one bad experience with a tiny bone left me feeling forever mistrustful of supposedly deboned ocean-going creatures. 
&lt;div class=&quot;col-md-6 image right&quot;&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;right horizontal&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://nicoladutoit.com/images/Merluccius_capensis.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;uncooked hake&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Let&#39;s face it, this is not a particularly scrumptious sight.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nonetheless, a combination of post-thesis time and some dietary discipline (in order to become a lean, mean running machine) have meant that The Boyfriend and I have been trying to diversify our low carb diet. In order to do so though, I’ve had to become decidedly less picky about what I eat. Enter the &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Merluccius_capensis&quot;&gt;hake&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few weeks ago we bought some &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.woolworths.co.za/store/fragments/product-details/product-details-index.jsp?productId=20012052&quot;&gt;frozen hake fillets from Woolworths&lt;/a&gt; (de-skinned and deboned) and our first attempt at frying it was edible but not hugely successful. Tonight I decided to try again, and after digging about online for some inspiration I decided I would improvise. This recipe is dead easy, healthy and quick to make, and turned out to be surprisingly bloody delicious. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Pan-fried hake&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Serves 4, or 2 very hungry people)
&lt;h3&gt;Ingredients&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;4 frozen hake pieces&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a bit of oil, for frying&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a clove of garlic&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;salt, pepper, ground paprika (or pretty much anything else you&#39;d like to use for flavour)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;butter&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a bit of plain flour&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a dash of lemon juice&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Instructions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;rinse the frozen fish and pat try with some kitchen towel (NB: don&#39;t defrost it!).&lt;/li&gt;	
&lt;li&gt;fry the garlic in some oil, and remove from the heat.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;melt a bit of butter in the microwave, and add the garlic, salt, pepper, paprika and lemon juice to the butter.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;baste the frozen fish pieces in the garlic butter mix.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;coat the basted fish pieces in flour.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;fry the fish in some sunflower oil until the outsides are brown and crispy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col-md-6 image center&quot;&gt;&lt;figure class=&quot;center horizontal&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://nicoladutoit.com/images/hake.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;battered, cooked hake&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;I suck at taking food photos but it looked pretty much like this. (Image by &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.flickr.com/photos/chodhound/4549921273/sizes/l/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;ChodHound&lt;/a&gt; on Flickr)&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
All the quantites are relative to how much fish you want to make (I had to melt a bit of extra butter to baste all the fish) but I don&#39;t think they need to be precisely measured out - just use common sense. I think it would go well with steamed veg, or just about any greens or salad. A nice, light, tasty meal!

(As an aside, I am quite appalled that I just blogged about food. This must be yet another symptom of my impending 30th birthday).




&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://nicoladutoit.com/articles/on-cooking-hake&quot;&gt;On cooking hake&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Nicola du Toit at &lt;a href=&quot;http://nicoladutoit.com&quot;&gt;Nicola du Toit&lt;/a&gt; on March 17, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[The UX design process]]></title>
  <link>http://nicoladutoit.com/articles/the-ux-design-process</link>
  <id>http://nicoladutoit.com/articles/the-ux-design-process</id>
  <updated>2014-01-28T00:00:00-00:00</updated>
  <published>2014-01-28T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  
  <author>
    <name>Nicola du Toit</name>
    <uri>http://nicoladutoit.com</uri>
    <email>nicoladutoit@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;There are many ways in which one can do design work. The usual process I follow in my current workplace is outlined here. Although I am a firm believer in a user-centred process, due to external time and financial constraints, some recent projects have included far less usability testing and market research than I would have liked. Different projects for different clients and teams require different approaches, but user requirements should always come first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Research&lt;/b&gt;: every project starts with research, be it into users, a brand, design guidelines and patterns, related products or all of the above. Before I draw a single sketch, I like to have an overview of who my users are, what they need to do, and how they should be able to do it. The result of this work is usually copious notes, use cases, workflows and a few possible site structures. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Ideate&lt;/b&gt;: once I have a clearer sense of my users and the scope of the project, I hit my notebook to brainstorm, sketch, doodle and think. I experiment with different ideas, iterating rapidly to do a creative dump of all the thoughts, chaotic notes and design options in my mind. I am usually able to narrow a new design down to one or two possibilities which will form the backbone of the project, in which case it’s time to start prototyping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Design&lt;/b&gt;: the official design process usually starts with paper prototypes that are the result of my initial brainstorming. Once a design starts taking shape on paper, I’ll couple it with sitemaps, wireframes and moodboards, to start putting flesh onto the project’s bare bones. I use different software depending on the fidelity of the mockups required. Sometimes hand drawn sketches suffice, but more often than not I land up working in Balsamiq, Inkscape or Photoshop because a picture really is worth a thousand words.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Brainstorming&lt;/b&gt;: once I have mockups in the bag, it’s time to sit down with my client (usually my employers and colleagues) and present my ideas. While it can be gruelling having a new design analysed and criticised, group discussions with team members and all involved parties provide invaluable insight and feedback. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Refinement&lt;/b&gt;: input from group sessions is used to improve the design, which usually requires some tweaking and editing. Improvements and further feedback usually occur in a number of iterations until everyone is happy with the final design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Final specification&lt;/b&gt;: much of the design work I currently do gets outsourced to external developers. If this is the case, depending on the project, the final brief will usually include a detailed technical specification, high-fidelity mockups, sitemaps and any other relevant technical or creative material that could be of use. Once everything has been collated it gets sent off to our developers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Development and testing&lt;/b&gt;: whether development happens in-house or externally the implementation phase typically involves many iterations of development, further changes to design, and thorough testing. At all stages of the design process, progress is cyclical and work needs to be continually revisited and reassessed!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;col-md-6 image center&quot;&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://nicoladutoit.com/images/post-it.jpg&quot; data-lightbox=&quot;post-its&quot; title=&quot;Brainstorming use cases and functionality&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://nicoladutoit.com/images/post-it.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;mapping site functionality with post-it notes&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://nicoladutoit.com/articles/the-ux-design-process&quot;&gt;The UX design process&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Nicola du Toit at &lt;a href=&quot;http://nicoladutoit.com&quot;&gt;Nicola du Toit&lt;/a&gt; on January 28, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tips for installing Jekyll with So Simple and Jekyll Slideshow]]></title>
  <link>http://nicoladutoit.com/articles/tips-for-installing-jekyll-with-so-simple-and-jekyll-slideshow</link>
  <id>http://nicoladutoit.com/articles/tips-for-installing-jekyll-with-so-simple-and-jekyll-slideshow</id>
  <updated>2014-01-16T00:00:00-00:00</updated>
  <published>2014-01-16T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  
  <author>
    <name>Nicola du Toit</name>
    <uri>http://nicoladutoit.com</uri>
    <email>nicoladutoit@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://jekyllrb.com/&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt; is my new favourite thing. I used it to build this site and most excitingly it integrates seamlessly with &lt;a href=&quot;http://github.com&quot;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;. There are a number of shiny themes available for Jekyll. This site uses the &lt;a href=&quot;http://mademistakes.com/articles/so-simple-jekyll-theme/&quot;&gt;So Simple Theme&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The processes for &lt;a href=&quot;http://jekyllrb.com/docs/installation/&quot;&gt;installing Jekyll&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mmistakes/so-simple-theme/&quot;&gt;installing this theme&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://help.github.com/articles/using-jekyll-with-pages&quot;&gt;using Jekyll with GitHub Pages&lt;/a&gt; are well documented and mostly simple, but I did run into a few weird errors when I added the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/matthewowen/jekyll-slideshow&quot;&gt;Jekyll Slideshow&lt;/a&gt; gallery plugin to my installation - I think due to version conflicts between all the different bits of software.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I managed to debug the process on my home laptop, then tried running Jekyll on my work machine and ran into the same problem. Stupidly, I couldn’t remember what the hell I’d done to fix it in the first place. For my own future reference and for your edification and delight, here is a list of commands that should install Jekyll, (Ruby and RubyGems), the So Simple theme and the Jekyll Slideshow plugin. These instructions should work for Ubuntu 12.04 and 13.10.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To install Jekyll you’ll first need to install Ruby and RubyGems:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo apt-get install ruby1.9.3
sudo apt-get install gem
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For good measure install the following Ruby extensions too:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo apt-get install libreadline-ruby1.9 libruby1.9 libopenssl-ruby
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then use RubyGems to install Jekyll:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo gem install jekyll
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once this is done, &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mmistakes/so-simple-theme/fork&quot;&gt;fork&lt;/a&gt; and clone the So Simple theme repo and follow the instructions &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mmistakes/so-simple-theme/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to customise and set up your new site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instructions for getting the Jekyll Slideshow plugin into your own repo are available &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/matthewowen/jekyll-slideshow&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. (Assuming you’re already using plugins, you’ll just need to copy across the &lt;code&gt;_plugins&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;jesl&lt;/code&gt; folders into your projects, and call some additional CSS.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jekyll Slideshow uses ImageMagick as well as the RMagick and nokogiri gems however, and this is where things started getting hairy for me but theoretically it should work if you’ve got the latest versions of everything on your machine. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ImageMagick is probably already installed if you’re in Ubuntu. To check:
    convert -version&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If it isn’t installed:
    sudo apt-get install imagemagick&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While you’re at it, also install the following library:
    sudo apt-get install libmagickwand-dev &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Assuming you’ve already copied the necessary bits of Jekyll Slideshow into your repo, you’ll need to install this plugins required gems:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo gem install rmagick
sudo gem install nokogiri
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Theoretically this should work. If it doesn’t, you might also want to try:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo apt-get install libxslt-dev libxml2-dev
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should now be able to build and serve up your Jekyll site (with a functional theme and plugin) using the &lt;a href=&quot;http://jekyllrb.com/docs/usage/&quot;&gt;standard Jekyll commands&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To integrate your new Jekyll repo with GitHub, you’ll also need to install Bundler:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo gem install bundler
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After this, create a file in your repo called &lt;code&gt;Gemfile&lt;/code&gt; and add the line &lt;code&gt;gem &#39;github-pages&#39;&lt;/code&gt;. Then run the command:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;bundle install.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suspect there may be an overlap between Bundler and the other gems I’ve installed, but following this process was the only way I could get everything to work, error free. &lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://nicoladutoit.com/articles/tips-for-installing-jekyll-with-so-simple-and-jekyll-slideshow&quot;&gt;Tips for installing Jekyll with So Simple and Jekyll Slideshow&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Nicola du Toit at &lt;a href=&quot;http://nicoladutoit.com&quot;&gt;Nicola du Toit&lt;/a&gt; on January 16, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why I love the Gautrain]]></title>
  <link>http://nicoladutoit.com/articles/why-i-love-the-gautrain</link>
  <id>http://nicoladutoit.com/articles/why-i-love-the-gautrain</id>
  <updated>2013-09-17T00:00:00-00:00</updated>
  <published>2013-11-14T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  
  <author>
    <name>Nicola du Toit</name>
    <uri>http://nicoladutoit.com</uri>
    <email>nicoladutoit@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I was 29 years old the first time I rode on a train in my hometown, &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Johannesburg&quot;&gt;Johannesburg&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To many people, this might sound like a strange fact, but white kids like me who grew up in the Southern end of the Northern ‘burbs in the 1980’s and 90’s didn’t take trains or buses or taxis. Public transport, where available, was notoriously complicated, unreliable and often just not safe. Why would you use it if your parents both had cars and were (mostly) willing to spend hours of their lives driving you around?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst there have always been trains going into Joburg and around Joburg, there have never been trains forming a network inside Joburg; trains that could get me to places I needed to be (in my Northern suburbs bubble); trains that could easily replace a parental vehicle. Joburg does not have century-old subterranean veins like London or Berlin or New York.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;col-md-6 image center&quot;&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/d/d7/London_Underground_1890.jpg&quot; data-lightbox=&quot;underground&quot;&gt;&lt;img border=&quot;0&quot; src=&quot;http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/d/d7/London_Underground_1890.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The London Underground in 1890&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Trains under the ground: not a thing in 1890&#39;s Joburg.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so, I grew up believing that trains were really a thing that only happened in England and Europe and the rest of the First World. I traveled on trains in London, Paris, Rome, Berlin, Singapore and California, before I stepped onto one in the city I have lived longest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I doubt very much that I will ever forget my first &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gautrain&quot;&gt;Gautrain&lt;/a&gt; trip from Sandton to O.R. Thambo airport. I was in Joburg for work - a 36 hour whirlwind trip - and by the time my mum had dropped me off at the station, I was tired and stressed out. She assured me that the ticket machines were really easy to use, but I knew I had to get a Gold Card (like London’s Oyster card) and preload it with the correct amount of money, then find the right platform, get on the right train and so on and so forth. This I have done countless times in foreign languages, in strange cities, in the dead of night, and here I was doing it for the first time in my home city, more nervous, clueless and overwhelmed than I’d ever been overseas, probably because I had no idea what to expect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Card and ticket bought, I was stunned by how user-friendly the machines were (mother is always right!). Things were looking up. I swiped my way through the turnstiles and then began the long escalator descent to Platform C, nine (!) floors underground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe I was on the 3rd long and steep, Tube-like escalator when I heard that unmistakable train-whooshing-in-a-tunnel sound. It was completely surreal. A First World, European noise in a mad, gritty African city! London in Johannesburg - how completely bizarre!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The train journey itself seemed like a dream - cutting over highways and intersections that I knew so well. Clean, safe and so fast! Fifteen minutes from Sandton to the airport?! This was the stuff of Joburg dreams when I was growing up! I believe I sent an inarticulate SMS to my mum saying something along the lines of “&lt;i&gt;Wheeeeeeeeeeeee!!!!!! Hehehe&lt;/i&gt;”. At the Ortia station, I walked straight into the airport feeling like I was in San Francisco again. I met my boss shortly afterwards and told him that I felt like a kid at Christmas. It was honestly one of the most exciting, exhilarating experiences I’d had all year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The novelty of taking a high speed train in my own city, in my own country! The novelty of safe, efficient public transport not only replacing a road trip, but shortening the commute to the Airport to a fraction of the time, not to mention the stress! The novelty of taking just a few minutes to travel dozens of kilometres during peak rush hour traffic! All of this excitement I put down to Gautrain-virgin glee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;col-md-6 image center&quot;&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://farm1.staticflickr.com/250/520316324_cdc8283982_z.jpg&quot; data-lightbox=&quot;jozi&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://farm1.staticflickr.com/250/520316324_cdc8283982_z.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Joburg traffic&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Joburg at rush hour: less appealing than triple bypass surgery.&lt;br /&gt;
Image by &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.flickr.com/photos/francapicc/&quot;&gt;jespahjoy&lt;/a&gt; on Flickr&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until yesterday, when (several months later) I caught the Gautrain to the airport and rode on a Joburg train for the second time in my entire life. And hearing that amazing train-whooshing-in-a-tunnel sound, again brought a lump to my throat and tears to my eyes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I realised yesterday that it is not a European or American noise, curiously displaced in an African city. It is not a London-in-Joburg sound. It is a Joburg-in-Joburg sound. It is the incredible sound of a country shifting gears and cruising along into the First World. It the sound of progress, burrowing away through the South African soil. Those tunnels smell of hope and progress and prosperity. The Gautrain is quite simply a symbol of South African future potential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;col-md-6 image center&quot;&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://nicoladutoit.com/images/gautrain.jpg&quot; data-lightbox=&quot;gautrain&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://nicoladutoit.com/images/gautrain.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The Gautrain, Ortia Station&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;21st century Joburg is a pretty shiny sight. &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my lifetime I have often wondered what this magnificent country would be like today if we didn’t have an appalling history of oppression and bigotry; if all South Africans had been permitted to realise their full potential for the last four centuries; and if democracy and capitalism had been the norm for hundreds of years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because we can’t undo history, I have also often wondered what future South Africa will be like. What will it be like to have efficient, affordable public transport for all? What will it be like when all of our citizens have homes and teachers and books and jobs? What will this country of Acacias and dust-rolling hills and smiles and dry bones and weathered hands feel like when it’s managed to heal its wounds?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Catching the Gautrain today, I realised that we are already watching the sun rise on those rolling green hills. Whilst the past and much of the present is still painful and complicated and difficult to fix, future South Africa is already here. It’s happening now, one train trip at a time, literally in the rich red soil beneath our feet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;col-md-6 image center&quot;&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8318/8023986234_5d22064db6_c.jpg&quot; data-lightbox=&quot;mountains&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8318/8023986234_5d22064db6_c.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Image by  &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.flickr.com/photos/wildlife_encounters/&quot; alt=&quot;Rolling green hills&quot;&gt;Steve Slater (Wildlife Encounters)&lt;/a&gt; on Flickr&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://nicoladutoit.com/articles/why-i-love-the-gautrain&quot;&gt;Why I love the Gautrain&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Nicola du Toit at &lt;a href=&quot;http://nicoladutoit.com&quot;&gt;Nicola du Toit&lt;/a&gt; on November 14, 2013.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Confessions of an atheist]]></title>
  <link>http://nicoladutoit.com/articles/confessions-of-an-atheist</link>
  <id>http://nicoladutoit.com/articles/confessions-of-an-atheist</id>
  <updated>2013-09-17T00:00:00-00:00</updated>
  <published>2013-09-17T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  
  <author>
    <name>Nicola du Toit</name>
    <uri>http://nicoladutoit.com</uri>
    <email>nicoladutoit@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I am an atheist. I went to an Anglican primary school, where we dutifully said our prayers and sang hymns every day, and believed our teachers when they told us we’d go to hell if we didn’t do our homework.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I was 10 years old, I was struck by lightning in an appalling accident that left four classmates dead. And, whilst 22 children were left reeling with post traumatic stress disorder &lt;strike&gt;months&lt;/strike&gt; years down the line, people justified this unthinkable trauma by saying that “God wanted four more angels to sing in his choir”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That was the beginning of the end of my relationship with the word and concept of “God”. I started to say “I believe in Science, not God”, and that’s largely true. It sounds so impressive, but so clinical. And what does it really mean?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One day, whilst drinking wine and watching birds in one of the loveliest corners of the Earth, I realised that life itself is simply amazing. The tenacity of things to grow, and reproduce; of cells to divide; of organisms to evolve, is extraordinary. We have gardens and forests and deserts and oceans and skies teeming with life. And life has been teeming for billions of years, with organisms that all have their place in a very complicated natural system. The genes handed down to me by my ancestors are uniquely my own, and yet I share DNA with every other person on Earth. Everything is connected and yet it is all unique.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;col-md-5 image center&quot;&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://nicoladutoit.com/images/brenton.JPG&quot; data-lightbox=&quot;brenton&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://nicoladutoit.com/images/brenton.JPG&quot; width=&quot;250&quot; alt=&quot;Brenton on Sea, Knysna&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Think of all the things living in this sea!&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Science, and human intellect and perseverance have enabled us to understand how much of this complicated system works, and that is amazing too. What clever organisms we’ve become! And on top of science, us humans have art, music, love, words, feats of profound endurance, loyalty, courage and compassion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it doesn’t end on Earth. I once met a person who declared that they simply couldn’t bear to look up at the night sky: they felt totally insignificant and overwhelmed. I look up at the stars and I feel elated. My soul soars at the knowledge that, as Carl Sagan so famously said, “we are all made of starstuff”. To look at a thousand tiny points of light, millions of years away, and know that we are part of all this and it is a part of us too…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;col-md-5 image center&quot;&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://imgsrc.hubblesite.org/hu/db/images/hs-2003-11-a-large_web.jpg&quot; data-lightbox=&quot;helix&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://imgsrc.hubblesite.org/hu/db/images/hs-2003-11-a-large_web.jpg&quot; width=&quot;300&quot; alt=&quot;The Helix Nebula, Hubble Telescope&quot; /&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;What&#39;s more incredible: that the &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Helix_Nebula&quot;&gt;Helix Nebula&lt;/a&gt; exists, or that we&#39;ve been able to photograph it using a telescope in space?&lt;br /&gt;
Image: &lt;a href=&quot;http://hubblesite.org/&quot;&gt;Hubble Telescope&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t need to believe in God to feel deeply connected to the world in which I live. Understanding how light reflects to create rainbows doesn’t diminish their beauty. Being able to analyse a Mahler symphony doesn’t make those wrenching harmonic progressions any less magnificent. Understanding photosynthesis doesn’t diminish the glory of a 400 year old tree.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Understanding does not diminish wonder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reality is awe inspiring. The world, solar system and universe in which we live is sensational, complicated, mysterious and beautiful. All we have to do is wake up and open our eyes to that which is busily being alive and extraordinary all around us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So then why do we, as a species, insist on believing in fairy tales, instead of in the magnificence of the real world?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Why is reality not enough?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or is reality simply too much for most people to stomach?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To quote Carl Sagan again:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Science is not only compatible with spirituality; it is a profound source of spirituality.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And because no post about the wondrousness of life is complete without wise words from Neil deGrasse Tyson (who says it better than I ever could):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/9D05ej8u-gU&quot; width=&quot;560&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://nicoladutoit.com/articles/confessions-of-an-atheist&quot;&gt;Confessions of an atheist&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Nicola du Toit at &lt;a href=&quot;http://nicoladutoit.com&quot;&gt;Nicola du Toit&lt;/a&gt; on September 17, 2013.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why I hate your bad grammar]]></title>
  <link>http://nicoladutoit.com/articles/why-i-hate-your-bad-grammar</link>
  <id>http://nicoladutoit.com/articles/why-i-hate-your-bad-grammar</id>
  <updated>2013-08-18T00:00:00-00:00</updated>
  <published>2013-08-18T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  
  <author>
    <name>Nicola du Toit</name>
    <uri>http://nicoladutoit.com</uri>
    <email>nicoladutoit@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I judge people based on their grammar, and here’s why: 
Language is arguably the most profound communication tool we &lt;i&gt;Homo sapiens&lt;/i&gt; have. Words have enabled us to share and pass on knowledge and learning for thousands and thousands of years. Words make us laugh, they make us weep and they make us rage. Words help us to describe and understand the world in which we live, and to communicate meaningfully with the rest of our species.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Words are not merely strings of letters, thrown together in random sequences. They are tasty, juicy brain-things, that can be manipulated and transformed to describe, elicit and enlighten. Language is a living, sweating, breathing beast. Grammar is the scaffold on which words hang, in beautiful strings of malleable, gleaming meaning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Knowingly using bad grammar and willfully neglecting spellcheckers or dictionaries (particularly in this day and age!) is like stomping through a flowerbed of spring bulbs because you’re too petulant and lazy to rather walk a bit further along a well-trodden path.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;col-md-5 image center&quot;&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://nicoladutoit.com/images/flowers.JPG&quot; data-lightbox=&quot;flowers&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://nicoladutoit.com/images/flowers.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;West coast National Park daisies in Spring&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;All these hateful flowerwords must die!&lt;br /&gt;
Because: fuck English!&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Call me a Grammar Nazi if you will. I prefer to think of myself as a well-educated, well-read linguaphile. I love words. I love reading them, speaking them, writing them, playing with them. They create worlds of meaning in which I have danced joyfully and wallowed luxuriously for years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love words in different languages. And I love the intricate meaning-space between languages. French verb conjugation fires up the puzzle-solving department in my brain. Earth-smelling Afrikaans descriptors regularly punch me in the gut. I recently saw a &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Malayalam&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Malayalam&lt;/a&gt; poetry book which, despite being in a foreign script, danced off the page with its beautiful symbols and symmetry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Words are my friends, my allies, my comfort in this chaotic world. They deserve to be treated with integrity and respect, not to be tossed around carelessly like tatty bits of garbage in the wind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Words are powerful&lt;/b&gt; and they should be wielded with care.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most often bad grammar just comes from a place of laziness. But sometimes, it stems from willful ignorance and this amounts to disrespect; disrespect for that which fundamentally differentiates us from our less articulate &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hominidae&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Hominid&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; cousins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this day and age there is simply no excuse for not understanding the difference between “to” and “too” or “there” and “their”. There exists an entire fucking Internet to show you how it’s done. If you know you’re doing it wrong, don’t laugh about it as if your illiteracy is cute. Get off your derrière and learn to speak and write your language properly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stop trashing the linguistic flowerbeds like a grunting gorilla and start walking along a grammatically-correct path like an articulate, intelligent human being.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;col-md-5 image center&quot;&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/a/aa/Dickens_Gurney_head.jpg/410px-Dickens_Gurney_head.jpg&quot; data-lightbox=&quot;Dickens&quot; title=&quot;That&#39;s Mr Dickens to you&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/a/aa/Dickens_Gurney_head.jpg/410px-Dickens_Gurney_head.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Charles Dickens&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;(I suspect &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles_Dickens&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;this man&lt;/a&gt; would agree.)&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Disclaimer: this post is in no way aimed at second or third language speakers or writers, or at people with legitimate language woes like dyslexia. It’s aimed at people who are supposedly fluent in their mother tongue, yet consistently (and knowingly) get their grammar and spelling wrong. We all make mistakes, but we can also learn from them. I’m not making any sweeping claims about my grammar being perfect, but I’d like to think I at least try to get it right…)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Note: if there are any typos of grammatical errors in this post, I shall run myself on a sword post-haste.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(&lt;b&gt;Edit&lt;/b&gt;: there was an “it’s” instead of an “its”. It has been fixed, and I’m nipping off to shoot myself now.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Other note: bad grammar online reminds me very much of this gem: &lt;a href=&quot;http://xkcd.com/386/&quot;&gt;http://xkcd.com/386/&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://nicoladutoit.com/articles/why-i-hate-your-bad-grammar&quot;&gt;Why I hate your bad grammar&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Nicola du Toit at &lt;a href=&quot;http://nicoladutoit.com&quot;&gt;Nicola du Toit&lt;/a&gt; on August 18, 2013.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[ZoneAlarm you're dead to me now]]></title>
  <link>http://nicoladutoit.com/articles/zonealarm-youre-dead-to-me-now</link>
  <id>http://nicoladutoit.com/articles/zonealarm-youre-dead-to-me-now</id>
  <updated>2013-08-14T00:00:00-00:00</updated>
  <published>2013-08-14T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  
  <author>
    <name>Nicola du Toit</name>
    <uri>http://nicoladutoit.com</uri>
    <email>nicoladutoit@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Having used &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.zonealarm.com/security/en-us/home.htm&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;ZoneAlarm&lt;/a&gt;’s free firewall in Windows for years and years, I just tried to upgrade, and got this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;col-md-10 image center&quot;&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://nicoladutoit.com/images/zonealarm.PNG&quot; data-lightbox=&quot;zonealarm&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://nicoladutoit.com/images/zonealarm.PNG&quot; alt=&quot;ZoneAlarm dark patterns&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“To enable “Agree” please check the two boxes below.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Set ZoneAlarm search as my home page and new tab for: All Browsers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Set ZoneAlarm Search as my default search provider for: All Browsers.&quot;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cheers ZoneAlarm. It’s been real.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would love to know how many users you’re going to lose thanks to your new policy of entrapment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Update: on uninstalling the damn thing, I was asked to provide customer feedback, so I did: “Remove the checkboxes, and I’ll reinstall your product.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://nicoladutoit.com/articles/zonealarm-youre-dead-to-me-now&quot;&gt;ZoneAlarm you're dead to me now&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Nicola du Toit at &lt;a href=&quot;http://nicoladutoit.com&quot;&gt;Nicola du Toit&lt;/a&gt; on August 14, 2013.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[So your hard drive crashed...]]></title>
  <link>http://nicoladutoit.com/articles/so-your-hard-drive-crashed</link>
  <id>http://nicoladutoit.com/articles/so-your-hard-drive-crashed</id>
  <updated>2013-02-06T00:00:00-00:00</updated>
  <published>2013-08-14T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  
  <author>
    <name>Nicola du Toit</name>
    <uri>http://nicoladutoit.com</uri>
    <email>nicoladutoit@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In the last couple of months I’ve had to listen to a number of friends and colleagues lamenting the recently-occured, or impending crash of their hard drive/flash disk/computer, resulting in a catastrophic loss of data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have two, highly unsympathetic words for them: &lt;b&gt;cloud storage&lt;/b&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;col-md-4 col-xs-6 image right&quot;&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5094/5472536812_c2dd4e93f6.jpg&quot; data-lightbox=&quot;drive&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5094/5472536812_c2dd4e93f6.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A hard drive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&quot;I&#39;m in your laptop. Flipping all your bits.&quot;&lt;br /&gt;
(Image by &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.flickr.com/photos/walkn/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;walknboston&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;on Flickr)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this day and age it is unbelievably easy to back up data. And not in the “copy it onto my five external drives and a DVD” sense of the word. I’m talking about syncing things into cyberspace, or, better still, actually creating them in cyberspace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hardware is fickle. &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bit_rot&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Bit rot&lt;/a&gt; is a bitch. As are &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cosmic_rays&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;cosmic rays&lt;/a&gt;.
Basically, any combination of silicon and solder ultimately results in failure, panic and tears.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this blog post is not about the untrustworthy nature of hardware. It’s about &lt;b&gt;why you should no longer care&lt;/b&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a stack of gleaming, cumulonimbus clouds out there in cyberspace which can and will save your bacon and your files. In no particular order, I give you the five current rockstars of online file storage and synchronization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://drive.google.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;1. Google Drive &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;col-md-3 image&quot;&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/a/ad/Logo_of_Google_Drive.svg/600px-Logo_of_Google_Drive.svg.png&quot; height=&quot;100&quot; width=&quot;100&quot; alt=&quot;Google Drive logo&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine a world in which Microsoft Office was free. A world in which you could make documents online, view them, edit them, have them automatically saved. Imagine being able to use version control on those documents - to roll back to earlier versions, or review your history. Now, imagine being able to access those documents on any one of your devices. And, just in case this wasn’t idyllic enough: imagine being able to share them with other people, who can then comment, edit, collaborate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enter the ninja: Google Drive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyone with a Google account has access to Google Drive. You get 15GB of storage for free (that’s a shit tonne of Word files, trust me) with the option to upgrade to 100GB for a whopping $4.99 per month. You never, &lt;b&gt;ever&lt;/b&gt; have to save a document again, and you never have to lose one either. Your docs will sync on basically any device (most of which let you edit too), and best of all, you can share them, let people comment on them, and author collaboratively and remotely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;col-md-5 right image&quot;&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://farm2.staticflickr.com/1191/543334336_dc24ebe65e_z.jpg&quot; data-lightbox=&quot;cloud&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://farm2.staticflickr.com/1191/543334336_dc24ebe65e_z.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Storm clouds&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Why hit Ctrl+S when you can write in the sky?&lt;br /&gt;
(&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.flickr.com/photos/nicholas_t/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Image by  Nicholas_T on Flickr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To give you one extreme use case: there’s a small start-up in Cape Town who &lt;b&gt;use Google Drive to author school textbooks&lt;/b&gt;. That’s right folks: they author entire textbooks using Google Drive. Documents are automatically saved. They are shared with multiple authors, who work remotely and can write, comment, collaborate and edit in the same document.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;2. GitHub&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;col-md-3 image right&quot;&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.global.ssl.fastly.net/images/modules/logos_page/Octocat.png&quot; width=&quot;200&quot; alt=&quot;GitHub logo&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Octocat is in your repo&lt;/a&gt;, watching all your things.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Github&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;: “GitHub is a web-based hosting service for software development projects that use the Git revision control system”. Git (the rock upon which GitHub is built) is revision control software, built by none other than &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Linus_Torvalds&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Linus Torvalds&lt;/a&gt; (of Linux kernel fame). GitHub is basically the king of version control. If you have a bunch of people working on the same files at the same time, this bad boy will keep track of all those changes, and merge them appropriately. Like most sensible cloud services, they offer free and paid versions too, depending on your privacy and size requirements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can roll back repositories, clone them, merge them, fork them… You can create, assign and track issues. You can view stunning visualizations of who’s changed what, where and when…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short: Linus Torvalds and the GitHub team deserve a repository-shaped cake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dropbox.com/&quot;&gt;3. Dropbox&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col-md-3 image&quot;&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://nicoladutoit.com/images/dropbox-logos_dropbox-vertical-blue.png&quot; alt=&quot;Dropbox logo&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those computer users who don’t trust Google, or don’t need the larny version control that GitHub has to offer, Dropbox is surely the most simple off-site storage solution. Dropbox gives you up to 18GB free (though friend referrals and social network sharing get you more data). After that, pricing starts at $10 per 100GB. Dropbox sits on your computer disguised as any other folder. And syncs the hell out of whatever happens in that folder. No need for backups, no need for tedious uploads. Dropbox will handle all of that for you. And, as with any well-synced data, you can access it from any device and from the web.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dropbox is ideal for lazy users, who, like me, want offsite syncing and backup that can babysit itself. I recently upgraded to a premium account and am syncing 75GB of photos. Because I like to sleep at night. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://evernote.com/&quot;&gt;4. Evernote&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col-md-4 col-xs-md-6 image&quot;&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://nicoladutoit.com/images/elephant.JPG&quot; data-lightbox=&quot;ellie&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://nicoladutoit.com/images/elephant.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;An elephant&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;A filing cabinet with ivory teeth.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Evernote is a brilliant tool for people who want to be organised. Content (in all shapes and sizes) can be organised into notebooks and folders, and labelled with tags. Imagine keeping track of a whack of PDF’s, web clippings and notes for a thesis literature review. Now imagine those same documents neatly filed and grouped, with searchable titles and tags. And now imagine all of this organisation being available to you on any device and on the web. Who needs a personal assistant when you have an elephant?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;col-md-3 image right&quot;&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://evernote.com/media/img/logos/evernote_logo_4c-sm.png&quot; alt=&quot;Evernote logo&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://evernote.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Evernote elephant&lt;/a&gt; has got you covered with his trunk.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Evernote also comes with a large suite of helper tools. The &lt;a href=&quot;http://evernote.com/webclipper/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Evernote web clipper&lt;/a&gt; is my favourite (for seamlessly saving bits of websites into my Evernote notebooks) but &lt;a href=&quot;http://evernote.com/skitch/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Skitch&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://evernote.com/penultimate/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Penultimate&lt;/a&gt; apparently come highly
recommended too. As with the other services, Evernote provides free access in exchange for (very reasonably) limited data, with premium, paid packages if you need more bandwidth. What’s not to love about this pachyderm?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.flickr.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;5. Flickr&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;col-md-4 image&quot;&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/7/78/Floppy_disc.jpg/794px-Floppy_disc.jpg&quot; data-lightbox=&quot;stiffy&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/7/78/Floppy_disc.jpg/794px-Floppy_disc.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A stiffy disk&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;You can store precisely no photos on one of these. (Image by&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:Floppy_disc.jpg&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Victor Korniyenko&lt;/a&gt; on WikiCommons)&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Up until fairly recently Flickr was cool for sharing photos, but in my books wouldn’t have merited a mention on a life-saving list like this. That was until they announced that anyone and everyone can now have &lt;b&gt;one free terabyte&lt;/b&gt; of storage on their site. That’s 1 000 000 000 000 bytes or 694 444 444 floppy disks (3/5 in 1.44 MB HD disks, to be precise). Flickr is the first site I know of to offer a tonne of free space like this, and hopefully, their new plan will put pressure on similar websites to do the same. (Dropbox, I’m looking at you!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike Dropbox, Flickr does not sync (i.e. you can upload only), and it’s only meant for photo and video sharing. But you can upload your digital media, neatly organised into sets, with tags and licensing, until the proverbial cows come home. Flickr displays your pics nicely as albums, and of course there’s a lot of community involved so you can easily share photos, write comments, join groups and so on. It takes some organisation and dedication to get set up but I know several people who are die-hard fans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This list is by no means meant to be exhaustive, but it is meant to be enlightening. There really is no excuse for data-loss related alcoholism and depression these days. As I type this, I am smug in the knowledge that my Masters’ dissertation and prototypes are tucked away in Google Drive (the writing bits), GitHub (the programming bits) and Evernote (the reading bits), and my photos are busily being uploaded into the Dropbox cyberspace, where they will be backed up on server after server and distributed into The Cloud.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;col-md-5 image center&quot;&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.google.com/about/datacenters/gallery/images/_2000/CBF_009.jpg&quot; data-lightbox=&quot;google&quot;&gt;&lt;img border=&quot;0&quot; src=&quot;http://www.google.com/about/datacenters/gallery/images/_2000/CBF_009.jpg&quot; lat=&quot;A Google data centre&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Not as portable as a USB hard drive but possibly more reliable.&lt;br /&gt;
(Image by&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.google.com/about/datacenters/gallery/#/tech/2&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Google&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://nicoladutoit.com/articles/so-your-hard-drive-crashed&quot;&gt;So your hard drive crashed...&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Nicola du Toit at &lt;a href=&quot;http://nicoladutoit.com&quot;&gt;Nicola du Toit&lt;/a&gt; on August 14, 2013.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Remembering how to run]]></title>
  <link>http://nicoladutoit.com/articles/remembering-how-to-run</link>
  <id>http://nicoladutoit.com/articles/remembering-how-to-run</id>
  <updated>2013-02-06T00:00:00-00:00</updated>
  <published>2013-04-10T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  
  <author>
    <name>Nicola du Toit</name>
    <uri>http://nicoladutoit.com</uri>
    <email>nicoladutoit@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;My original intention for resurrecting my blog was to write about tech-ified things. But, life is far more interesting and varied than that, so here’s a story about how I recently started remembering how to run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;col-md-5 col-xs-12 image right&quot;&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7035/6808990081_2d728abc1c_m.jpg&quot; data-lightbox=&quot;biker&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7035/6808990081_2d728abc1c_m.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;This man is probably on drugs. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.flickr.com/photos/mdpettitt/6808990081/in/photostream/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Image: Martin Pettitt on Flickr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have never been a fan of exercise. In high school I traded in Physical Education for music lessons at the first possible opportunity.  I’ve always judged people who run marathons, swim kilometres, cycle races (OK, I still judge cyclists but that’s Lance Armstrong’s fault). I was convinced they were all obsessed, insane motherfuckers. Why the hell would you go running at the end of a tough day, when you could have a glass of wine and watch the sunset like a reasonable person?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;col-md-4 image&quot;&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;a href=&quot;http://nicoladutoit.com/images/dogs.jpg&quot; data-lightbox=&quot;dogs&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://nicoladutoit.com/images/dogs.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;These aren&#39;t high maintenance dogs at all.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My disdain for exercise (with the exception of dog walking, which is a necessity with two hyper Rough Collies) and very sloppy eating habits inevitably resulted in the gradual expansion of my (and the Boyfriend’s) waistline. At the end of 2011, we both decided something had to be done, and so we started &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mujaji.org.za/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;dragonboating&lt;/a&gt; (an awesome story for another day). At the beginning of 2012 after some alarming blood tests, we also overhauled our diet, and we both started fittening up and slimming down. Things stalled in the middle of the year though (winter, work, stress) and although we didn’t regain weight, the weight loss process stagnated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so, at the beginning of this year, we decided to try again - we knew that a combination of intense exercise and healthy eating had worked for us before. We already had a mountainous dog-walking loop on the slopes of Table Mountain. We just had to make a concerted effort to get there several times a week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;col-md-4 image right&quot;&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;a href=&quot;http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3080/2462288281_2b18b17296_n.jpg&quot; data-lightbox=&quot;climbing&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3080/2462288281_2b18b17296_n.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;That&#39;s me walking my dogs, up a vertical rock face. (Dogs not included)&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.flickr.com/photos/lynnmwillis/2462288281/sizes/n/in/photostream/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Image: lynnmwillis on Flickr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first few weeks were terrible. To be sure, our usual route is no amble in the forest - it’s steep, rocky, hilly (it really is on the slopes of a substantial mountain). Nonetheless, I felt like Sir Edmund Hilary climbing bloody Everest. My legs ached with every step. My lungs raged against me. Tears welled up in my eyes at the sight of some of those uphill slopes. I trailed miserably behind Boyfriend, who is much better acclimatised to walking than me. I may have been paddling-fit from all the dragonboat training, but I sucked at walking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not long after we hit the forest again, we paddled in a big dragonboating regatta, and our club narrowly lost out on some gold medals, much to our disappointment. We realised that we needed to become all-round fit and lose some more kilos, in order to paddle harder. Shortly after, we also quit smoking (that’s another awesome story for another day - suffice to say that it’s been 5 weeks and I’m feeling totally fantastic!). I suspect I’ll look back and say that quitting smoking and losing those gold medals was the beginning of my running career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;col-md-5 image&quot;&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;a href=&quot;http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8330/8113284229_a8abdc5721_n.jpg&quot; data-lightbox=&quot;shins&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8330/8113284229_a8abdc5721_n.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;It turns out that shins are real pricks.
Not as big pricks as cigarettes though.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.flickr.com/photos/tabor-roeder/8113284229/sizes/n/in/photostream/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Image: Phil Roeder on Flickr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We know many people who run (whom I used to think were clinically insane, but now have huge respect for), who all gave us the same advice: take it slowly. So, I started out only trying to run on the flat bits. And then my shins ached and I had to stop. I experimented with different gaits, cadences, speeds, breathing. It all felt horrible, awkward, even worse than the walking. But I persevered. Every time I could run a little bit further before it felt like my shins were going to implode, or before I started hyperventilating and seeing the forest in tunnel-shaped shades of grey. And every time the walking in between became noticeably easier (I can now comfortably power walk at boyfriend’s pace).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;col-md-4 col-xs-12 image right&quot;&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;a href=&quot;http://farm1.staticflickr.com/47/127206671_3cbfa594fc_n.jpg&quot; data-lightbox=&quot;keef&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://farm1.staticflickr.com/47/127206671_3cbfa594fc_n.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Keith Richards is my running coach.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.flickr.com/photos/julio_/127206671/sizes/n/in/photostream/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Image: Julius! on Flickr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One day, whilst listening to The Rollin’ Stones “Jumpin’ Jack Flash” I found myself running down a very long hill, and nothing hurt. My heart rate was stable. I looked up at the clouds through the trees and felt like I was floating through the woods. I realised if I could find that sweet spot just once, briefly, I could find it again. And I have, almost every time we’ve been back (unless we’re just walking on a rest day).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last week I had the pleasure of receiving new running shoes for my birthday (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.adidas.com/us/product/womens-running-kanadia-5-trail-shoes/CF342?cid=Q22384&amp;amp;breadcrumb=svZu3Z1z13y9lZ1z13071&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Adidas Kanadia TR5&lt;/a&gt;’s - my beloved Salomon’s were totally shot) and I came up with a simple training plan (run this flat bit first, then that flat bit, then that bit in between. Then add that bit of downhill, and so on…). Today I nailed a nasty uphill, and literally “whooped” when I got to the top. I was sucking air like a vacuum cleaner and my lungs were pumping lava, but I was triumphant. A year ago I had wept, plodding slowly up that same shitty hill because it seemed so steep and I was so close to despair.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m aiming to run our entire loop one of these days. And then I’m going to run it twice, and then I’m going to enter a 5km trail run. That’s my running saga to date. (Edit: See update below.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;col-md-5 image center&quot;&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;a href=&quot;http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8281/7734344062_abdbb67a6d_n.jpg&quot; data-lightbox=&quot;bolt&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8281/7734344062_abdbb67a6d_n.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Future me is a speedy, black Jamaican man.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.flickr.com/photos/nickwebb/7734344062/sizes/n/in/photostream/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Image: Nick J Webb on Flickr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The running is part of a bigger process though, that’s turning out to be a new journey with myself. I realised today that I am much, much tougher than I thought. I can push myself harder than I’d ever expected. My comfort zone is expanding by the day. I’m no longer scared of falling on my face, or losing control of my legs, or slipping and landing on my arse. In fact, I &lt;i&gt;love&lt;/i&gt; the feeling of free-wheeling on my own two feet. I’m not afraid of the discomfort of burning lungs and aching muscles. Running up that damn hill today, it felt like a whole world of possibilities was literally unfurling before me with each step. And it felt like I was returning to that gleeful comfortable-in-my-body, fierce fearlessness that I knew and loved as a kid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;col-md-4 image center&quot;&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;a href=&quot;http://nicoladutoit.com/images/OubosRock.jpg&quot; data-lightbox=&quot;oubos&quot;&gt; &lt;img src=&quot;http://nicoladutoit.com/images/OubosRock.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Fearless, fierce me (no really) embarking on my rock climbing career, aged 3.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A colleague who recently ran the 56km &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.twooceansmarathon.org.za/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Two Oceans Ultra Marathon&lt;/a&gt; said to me today:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“You run with your mind, not with your legs.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We all knew how to run when we were kids. Why do we apparently forget how to do it when we grow up? I don’t think our legs forget - we’re animals after all. I think at some point we stop running and then our minds become fearful. I think mostly, we fear failure, and we avoid trying the things that we fear. And then we forget that once upon a time, these were things we loved, relished and did with joy… Learning how to run is not something new, it’s something old (in the personal and evolutionary sense). It’s a return to something wonderful that I used to be able to do. It’s remembering what has happened before, and forgetting the fear about what is still to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;col-md-5 image center&quot;&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;a href=&quot;http://nicoladutoit.com/images/newlands.jpg&quot; data-lightbox=&quot;gym&quot;&gt; &lt;img src=&quot;http://nicoladutoit.com/images/newlands.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Boyfriend and dogs, in our really shitty gym.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Update (July 2013): Since writing this post, I have had an absolute blast running the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.vws.org.za/?p=3234&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Volunteer Wildfire Services 10km trail run&lt;/a&gt; on the slopes of Table Mountain and the 11 km &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.magneticsouth.net/events/salomon-featherbed-trail-run/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Salomon Featherbed Seahorse trail run&lt;/a&gt; in Knysna. Next up is the &lt;a href=&quot;http://trailrunning.co.za/events_detail.php?id=710&amp;amp;type=current&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Salomon Bastille Day trail run&lt;/a&gt; this weekend! Bring on them mountains! I’ve also had this blog post published in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gomulti.co.za/2013/06/18/issue-7-trail-magazine-released/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;July edition of Trail&lt;/a&gt; magazine. Yay!&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://nicoladutoit.com/articles/remembering-how-to-run&quot;&gt;Remembering how to run&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Nicola du Toit at &lt;a href=&quot;http://nicoladutoit.com&quot;&gt;Nicola du Toit&lt;/a&gt; on April 10, 2013.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why CC-BY-SA should die]]></title>
  <link>http://nicoladutoit.com/articles/why-cc-by-sa-should-die</link>
  <id>http://nicoladutoit.com/articles/why-cc-by-sa-should-die</id>
  <updated>2013-02-06T00:00:00-00:00</updated>
  <published>2013-03-28T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  
  <author>
    <name>Nicola du Toit</name>
    <uri>http://nicoladutoit.com</uri>
    <email>nicoladutoit@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Creative commons copyright licenses are, in a nutshell, awesome. They offer flexibile, standardised, &lt;b&gt;open&lt;/b&gt;, alternatives to the miserable “ © All Rights Reserved” that is so prevalent in the world today. I’m not going to go into detail here about how copyright licenses are generally misused. I am, however, going to complain about how one particular open license is commonly used, and why that usage sucks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to creative commons (&lt;a href=&quot;http://creativecommons.org/licenses/&quot;&gt;http://creativecommons.org/licenses/&lt;/a&gt;), the Attribution-ShareAlike CC-BY-SA license:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;lets others remix, tweak, and build upon your work even for commercial 
purposes, as long as they credit you and license their new creations 
under the identical terms. This license is often compared to “copyleft” 
free and open source software licenses. All new works based on yours will carry the same license, so any derivatives will also allow commercial use. This is the license used by Wikipedia, and is recommended for materials that would benefit from incorporating content from Wikipedia and similarly licensed projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This sounds very noble in principle. People have to share your material under the same license, which means it will always remain openly licensed. A good thing, surely? &lt;b&gt;Not always&lt;/b&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a common use case for when it goes horribly wrong:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you upload a photo to Flickr, the default “open” license option is CC-BY-SA. This results in the vast majority of openly-licensed photos on Flickr being filed under this license. (The same applies, to an even greater extent, to Wikimedia content and the comparable GNU license). However, you cannot use CC-BY-SA licensed material under the &lt;b&gt;more open&lt;/b&gt; CC-BY license!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most users will probably be blissfully unaware of this unfortunate caveat. I suspect those unfamiliar with open licenses go “oh, this is cool” without realising that CC-BY-SA is actually a ‘closed’ license for those of us who work in the CC-BY or public domain arena.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The simple two-step solution: firstly, the default licensing-on-upload option on huge repos like Wikimedia and Flickr needs to change (to be more open!) and secondly users of such sites need to be better educated about their licensing options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We no longer live in a black and white world of closed vs. open. Open licensing has expanded to include many different flavours of openness. It’s just a pity that some of those flavours act on others in a ‘closed’ way.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://nicoladutoit.com/articles/why-cc-by-sa-should-die&quot;&gt;Why CC-BY-SA should die&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Nicola du Toit at &lt;a href=&quot;http://nicoladutoit.com&quot;&gt;Nicola du Toit&lt;/a&gt; on March 28, 2013.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[To blog or to press]]></title>
  <link>http://nicoladutoit.com/articles/to-blog-or-to-press</link>
  <id>http://nicoladutoit.com/articles/to-blog-or-to-press</id>
  <updated>2013-02-06T00:00:00-00:00</updated>
  <published>2013-02-06T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  
  <author>
    <name>Nicola du Toit</name>
    <uri>http://nicoladutoit.com</uri>
    <email>nicoladutoit@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve had a number of cool ideas for blog posts recently, and so decided to log in to my very rusty Wordpress and Blogger accounts and see if I could resurrect an old blog to start writing again.
 (This was long before my eyes had been opened to human-computer interaction and user-centered design). Needless to say, I am now absolutely stunned to see how far Blogger has come in the 3-or-so years since I last used it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For one, Blogger has a much more “Googley” feel than it used to - for someone who uses GDocs a lot, even the fonts and menus look familiar, so I immediately had some idea of what to expect. Predictability and familiarity - tick. It’s curious that it took Google so long to update Blogger. They bought the company in 2002, but in 2008 Blogger was still very tedious to use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moving on, customising the theme for my new blog was a doddle, with lots of advanced options (including an option to edit the HTML direct). Deleting and editing my decayed old blogs was really easy to do, and generally the whole website seemed much simpler to use than Wordpress. (The devil is in the detail, for example: Wordpress uses “tags”. Blogger uses “labels”, which I know and love from my daily use of Gmail).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also love the Google+ integration. I’m not a huge Google+ user but given &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.searchenginejournal.com/google-plus-surpasses-twitter-to-become-second-largest-social-network/57740/&quot;&gt;it’s now the second most popular social network&lt;/a&gt;, this kind of seamless integration is probably going to be really useful in the near future. And I don’t even have to think about installing silly plugins that will allow people to tweet, Facebook or RSS my posts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then of course there’s Blogger’s cute little WYSIWYG blog post editor… I doubt it does fancy stuff like maths equations at this point, but it sure beats Wordpress’ TinyMCE, which has been the bane of my existence for many years. (As far as I’m concerned, the only useful button TinyMCE provides is the “HTML” button, for raw editing). and again, as a GDocs user, it’s really familiar and easy to use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post has been a bit of an experiment - so far I’ve been far more impressed by Blogger’s new look and feel than by my clunky old Wordpress account. I’m going to continue my little impromptu user test and publish this quickly…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Edit&lt;/b&gt;: Blogger even comes with baby Google Analytics bolted into the background. So far I’m impressed!&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://nicoladutoit.com/articles/to-blog-or-to-press&quot;&gt;To blog or to press&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Nicola du Toit at &lt;a href=&quot;http://nicoladutoit.com&quot;&gt;Nicola du Toit&lt;/a&gt; on February 06, 2013.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>

</feed>
