<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
<title type="text">Nicola du Toit</title>
<generator uri="https://github.com/mojombo/jekyll">Jekyll</generator>
<link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" />
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://localhost:4000" />
<updated>2014-01-11T21:53:42+02:00</updated>
<id>http://localhost:4000/</id>
<author>
  <name>Nicola du Toit</name>
  <uri>http://localhost:4000/</uri>
  <email>nicoladutoit@gmail.com</email>
</author>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[ZoneAlarm you're dead to me now.]]></title>
  <link>http://localhost:4000/articles/zonealarm-youre-dead-to-me-now</link>
  <id>http://localhost:4000/articles/zonealarm-youre-dead-to-me-now</id>
  <updated>2013-08-14T00:00:00-00:00</updated>
  <published>2013-08-14T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  
  <author>
    <name>Nicola du Toit</name>
    <uri>http://localhost:4000</uri>
    <email>nicoladutoit@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Having used &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.zonealarm.com/security/en-us/home.htm&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;ZoneAlarm&lt;/a&gt;’s free firewall in Windows for years and years, I just tried to upgrade, and got this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blog/zonealarm.PNG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“To enable “Agree” please check the two boxes below.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Set ZoneAlarm search as my home page and new tab for: All Browsers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Set ZoneAlarm Search as my default search provider for: All Browsers.&quot;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cheers ZoneAlarm. It’s been real.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would love to know how many users you’re going to lose thanks to your new policy of entrapment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Update: on uninstalling the damn thing, I was asked to provide customer feedback, so I did: “Remove the checkboxes, and I’ll reinstall your product.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://localhost:4000/articles/zonealarm-youre-dead-to-me-now&quot;&gt;ZoneAlarm you're dead to me now.&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Nicola du Toit at &lt;a href=&quot;http://localhost:4000&quot;&gt;Nicola du Toit&lt;/a&gt; on August 14, 2013.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Remembering how to run]]></title>
  <link>http://localhost:4000/articles/remembering-how-to-run</link>
  <id>http://localhost:4000/articles/remembering-how-to-run</id>
  <updated>2013-02-06T00:00:00-00:00</updated>
  <published>2013-04-10T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  
  <author>
    <name>Nicola du Toit</name>
    <uri>http://localhost:4000</uri>
    <email>nicoladutoit@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;My original intention for resurrecting my blog was to write about tech-ified things. But, life is far more interesting and varied than that, so here’s a story about how I recently started remembering how to run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;right horizontal&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7035/6808990081_2d728abc1c_m.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;This man is probably on drugs. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.flickr.com/photos/mdpettitt/6808990081/in/photostream/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Image: Martin Pettitt on Flickr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have never been a fan of exercise. In high school I traded in Physical Education for music lessons at the first possible opportunity.  I’ve always judged people who run marathons, swim kilometres, cycle races (OK, I still judge cyclists but that’s Lance Armstrong’s fault). I was convinced they were all obsessed, insane motherfuckers. Why the hell would you go running at the end of a tough day, when you could have a glass of wine and watch the sunset like a reasonable person?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;left vertical&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blog/dogs.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;These aren't high maintenance dogs at all.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My disdain for exercise (with the exception of dog walking, which is a necessity with two hyper Rough Collies) and very sloppy eating habits inevitably resulted in the gradual expansion of my (and the Boyfriend’s) waistline. At the end of 2011, we both decided something had to be done, and so we started &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mujaji.org.za/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;dragonboating&lt;/a&gt; (an awesome story for another day). At the beginning of 2012 after some alarming blood tests, we also overhauled our diet, and we both started fittening up and slimming down. Things stalled in the middle of the year though (winter, work, stress) and although we didn’t regain weight, the weight loss process stagnated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so, at the beginning of this year, we decided to try again - we knew that a combination of intense exercise and healthy eating had worked for us before. We already had a mountainous dog-walking loop on the slopes of Table Mountain. We just had to make a concerted effort to get there several times a week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;right vertical&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3080/2462288281_2b18b17296_n.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;That's me walking my dogs, up a vertical rock face. (Dogs not included)&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.flickr.com/photos/lynnmwillis/2462288281/sizes/n/in/photostream/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Image: lynnmwillis on Flickr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first few weeks were terrible. To be sure, our usual route is no amble in the forest - it’s steep, rocky, hilly (it really is on the slopes of a substantial mountain). Nonetheless, I felt like Sir Edmund Hilary climbing bloody Everest. My legs ached with every step. My lungs raged against me. Tears welled up in my eyes at the sight of some of those uphill slopes. I trailed miserably behind Boyfriend, who is much better acclimatised to walking than me. I may have been paddling-fit from all the dragonboat training, but I sucked at walking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not long after we hit the forest again, we paddled in a big dragonboating regatta, and our club narrowly lost out on some gold medals, much to our disappointment. We realised that we needed to become all-round fit and lose some more kilos, in order to paddle harder. Shortly after, we also quit smoking (that’s another awesome story for another day - suffice to say that it’s been 5 weeks and I’m feeling totally fantastic!). I suspect I’ll look back and say that quitting smoking and losing those gold medals was the beginning of my running career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;left horizontal&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8330/8113284229_a8abdc5721_n.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;It turns out that shins are real pricks.
Not as big pricks as cigarettes though.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.flickr.com/photos/tabor-roeder/8113284229/sizes/n/in/photostream/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Image: Phil Roeder on Flickr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We know many people who run (whom I used to think were clinically insane, but now have huge respect for), who all gave us the same advice: take it slowly. So, I started out only trying to run on the flat bits. And then my shins ached and I had to stop. I experimented with different gaits, cadences, speeds, breathing. It all felt horrible, awkward, even worse than the walking. But I persevered. Every time I could run a little bit further before it felt like my shins were going to implode, or before I started hyperventilating and seeing the forest in tunnel-shaped shades of grey. And every time the walking in between became noticeably easier (I can now comfortably power walk at boyfriend’s pace).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;right vertical&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;http://farm1.staticflickr.com/47/127206671_3cbfa594fc_n.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Keith Richards is my running coach.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.flickr.com/photos/julio_/127206671/sizes/n/in/photostream/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Image: Julius! on Flickr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One day, whilst listening to The Rollin’ Stones “Jumpin’ Jack Flash” I found myself running down a very long hill, and nothing hurt. My heart rate was stable. I looked up at the clouds through the trees and felt like I was floating through the woods. I realised if I could find that sweet spot just once, briefly, I could find it again. And I have, almost every time we’ve been back (unless we’re just walking on a rest day).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last week I had the pleasure of receiving new running shoes for my birthday (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.adidas.com/us/product/womens-running-kanadia-5-trail-shoes/CF342?cid=Q22384&amp;amp;breadcrumb=svZu3Z1z13y9lZ1z13071&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Adidas Kanadia TR5&lt;/a&gt;’s - my beloved Salomon’s were totally shot) and I came up with a simple training plan (run this flat bit first, then that flat bit, then that bit in between. Then add that bit of downhill, and so on…). Today I nailed a nasty uphill, and literally “whooped” when I got to the top. I was sucking air like a vacuum cleaner and my lungs were pumping lava, but I was triumphant. A year ago I had wept, plodding slowly up that same shitty hill because it seemed so steep and I was so close to despair.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m aiming to run our entire loop one of these days. And then I’m going to run it twice, and then I’m going to enter a 5km trail run. That’s my running saga to date. (Edit: See update below.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center horizontal&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8281/7734344062_abdbb67a6d_n.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Future me is a speedy, black Jamaican man.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.flickr.com/photos/nickwebb/7734344062/sizes/n/in/photostream/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Image: Nick J Webb on Flickr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The running is part of a bigger process though, that’s turning out to be a new journey with myself. I realised today that I am much, much tougher than I thought. I can push myself harder than I’d ever expected. My comfort zone is expanding by the day. I’m no longer scared of falling on my face, or losing control of my legs, or slipping and landing on my arse. In fact, I &lt;i&gt;love&lt;/i&gt; the feeling of free-wheeling on my own two feet. I’m not afraid of the discomfort of burning lungs and aching muscles. Running up that damn hill today, it felt like a whole world of possibilities was literally unfurling before me with each step. And it felt like I was returning to that gleeful comfortable-in-my-body, fierce fearlessness that I knew and loved as a kid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center vertical&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blog/OubosRock.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Fearless, fierce me (no really) embarking on my rock climbing career, aged 3.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A colleague who recently ran the 56km &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.twooceansmarathon.org.za/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Two Oceans Ultra Marathon&lt;/a&gt; said to me today:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“You run with your mind, not with your legs.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We all knew how to run when we were kids. Why do we apparently forget how to do it when we grow up? I don’t think our legs forget - we’re animals after all. I think at some point we stop running and then our minds become fearful. I think mostly, we fear failure, and we avoid trying the things that we fear. And then we forget that once upon a time, these were things we loved, relished and did with joy… Learning how to run is not something new, it’s something old (in the personal and evolutionary sense). It’s a return to something wonderful that I used to be able to do. It’s remembering what has happened before, and forgetting the fear about what is still to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center vertical&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blog/newlands.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Boyfriend and dogs, in our really shitty gym.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Update (July 2013): Since writing this post, I have had an absolute blast running the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.vws.org.za/?p=3234&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Volunteer Wildfire Services 10km trail run&lt;/a&gt; on the slopes of Table Mountain and the 11 km &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.magneticsouth.net/events/salomon-featherbed-trail-run/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Salomon Featherbed Seahorse trail run&lt;/a&gt; in Knysna. Next up is the &lt;a href=&quot;http://trailrunning.co.za/events_detail.php?id=710&amp;amp;type=current&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Salomon Bastille Day trail run&lt;/a&gt; this weekend! Bring on them mountains! I’ve also had this blog post published in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gomulti.co.za/2013/06/18/issue-7-trail-magazine-released/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;July edition of Trail&lt;/a&gt; magazine. Yay!&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://localhost:4000/articles/remembering-how-to-run&quot;&gt;Remembering how to run&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Nicola du Toit at &lt;a href=&quot;http://localhost:4000&quot;&gt;Nicola du Toit&lt;/a&gt; on April 10, 2013.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why CC-BY-SA should die]]></title>
  <link>http://localhost:4000/articles/why-cc-by-sa-should-die</link>
  <id>http://localhost:4000/articles/why-cc-by-sa-should-die</id>
  <updated>2013-02-06T00:00:00-00:00</updated>
  <published>2013-03-28T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  
  <author>
    <name>Nicola du Toit</name>
    <uri>http://localhost:4000</uri>
    <email>nicoladutoit@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Creative commons copyright licenses are, in a nutshell, awesome. They offer flexibile, standardised, &lt;b&gt;open&lt;/b&gt;, alternatives to the miserable “ © All Rights Reserved” that is so prevalent in the world today. I’m not going to go into detail here about how copyright licenses are generally misused. I am, however, going to complain about how one particular open license is commonly used, and why that usage sucks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to creative commons (&lt;a href=&quot;http://creativecommons.org/licenses/&quot;&gt;http://creativecommons.org/licenses/&lt;/a&gt;), the Attribution-ShareAlike CC-BY-SA license:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;lets others remix, tweak, and build upon your work even for commercial 
purposes, as long as they credit you and license their new creations 
under the identical terms. This license is often compared to “copyleft” 
free and open source software licenses. All new works based on yours will carry the same license, so any derivatives will also allow commercial use. This is the license used by Wikipedia, and is recommended for materials that would benefit from incorporating content from Wikipedia and similarly licensed projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This sounds very noble in principle. People have to share your material under the same license, which means it will always remain openly licensed. A good thing, surely? &lt;b&gt;Not always&lt;/b&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a common use case for when it goes horribly wrong:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you upload a photo to Flickr, the default “open” license option is CC-BY-SA. This results in the vast majority of openly-licensed photos on Flickr being filed under this license. (The same applies, to an even greater extent, to Wikimedia content and the comparable GNU license). However, you cannot use CC-BY-SA licensed material under the &lt;b&gt;more open&lt;/b&gt; CC-BY license!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most users will probably be blissfully unaware of this unfortunate caveat. I suspect those unfamiliar with open licenses go “oh, this is cool” without realising that CC-BY-SA is actually a ‘closed’ license for those of us who work in the CC-BY or public domain arena.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The simple two-step solution: firstly, the default licensing-on-upload option on huge repos like Wikimedia and Flickr needs to change (to be more open!) and secondly users of such sites need to be better educated about their licensing options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We no longer live in a black and white world of closed vs. open. Open licensing has expanded to include many different flavours of openness. It’s just a pity that some of those flavours act on others in a ‘closed’ way.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://localhost:4000/articles/why-cc-by-sa-should-die&quot;&gt;Why CC-BY-SA should die&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Nicola du Toit at &lt;a href=&quot;http://localhost:4000&quot;&gt;Nicola du Toit&lt;/a&gt; on March 28, 2013.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[To blog or to press]]></title>
  <link>http://localhost:4000/articles/to-blog-or-to-press</link>
  <id>http://localhost:4000/articles/to-blog-or-to-press</id>
  <updated>2013-02-06T00:00:00-00:00</updated>
  <published>2013-02-06T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  
  <author>
    <name>Nicola du Toit</name>
    <uri>http://localhost:4000</uri>
    <email>nicoladutoit@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve had a number of cool ideas for blog posts recently, and so decided to log in to my very rusty Wordpress and Blogger accounts and see if I could resurrect an old blog to start writing again.
 (This was long before my eyes had been opened to human-computer interaction and user-centered design). Needless to say, I am now absolutely stunned to see how far Blogger has come in the 3-or-so years since I last used it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For one, Blogger has a much more “Googley” feel than it used to - for someone who uses GDocs a lot, even the fonts and menus look familiar, so I immediately had some idea of what to expect. Predictability and familiarity - tick. It’s curious that it took Google so long to update Blogger. They bought the company in 2002, but in 2008 Blogger was still very tedious to use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moving on, customising the theme for my new blog was a doddle, with lots of advanced options (including an option to edit the HTML direct). Deleting and editing my decayed old blogs was really easy to do, and generally the whole website seemed much simpler to use than Wordpress. (The devil is in the detail, for example: Wordpress uses “tags”. Blogger uses “labels”, which I know and love from my daily use of Gmail).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also love the Google+ integration. I’m not a huge Google+ user but given &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.searchenginejournal.com/google-plus-surpasses-twitter-to-become-second-largest-social-network/57740/&quot;&gt;it’s now the second most popular social network&lt;/a&gt;, this kind of seamless integration is probably going to be really useful in the near future. And I don’t even have to think about installing silly plugins that will allow people to tweet, Facebook or RSS my posts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then of course there’s Blogger’s cute little WYSIWYG blog post editor… I doubt it does fancy stuff like maths equations at this point, but it sure beats Wordpress’ TinyMCE, which has been the bane of my existence for many years. (As far as I’m concerned, the only useful button TinyMCE provides is the “HTML” button, for raw editing). and again, as a GDocs user, it’s really familiar and easy to use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post has been a bit of an experiment - so far I’ve been far more impressed by Blogger’s new look and feel than by my clunky old Wordpress account. I’m going to continue my little impromptu user test and publish this quickly…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Edit&lt;/b&gt;: Blogger even comes with baby Google Analytics bolted into the background. So far I’m impressed!&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://localhost:4000/articles/to-blog-or-to-press&quot;&gt;To blog or to press&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Nicola du Toit at &lt;a href=&quot;http://localhost:4000&quot;&gt;Nicola du Toit&lt;/a&gt; on February 06, 2013.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>

</feed>
