<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
<title type="text">Nicola du Toit</title>
<generator uri="https://github.com/mojombo/jekyll">Jekyll</generator>
<link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="/feed.xml" />
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="" />
<updated>2015-11-23T13:13:37+02:00</updated>
<id>/</id>
<author>
  <name>Nicola du Toit</name>
  <uri>/</uri>
  <email>nicoladutoit@gmail.com</email>
</author>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to survive a dissertation]]></title>
  <link>/articles/how-to-survive-a-dissertation</link>
  <id>/articles/how-to-survive-a-dissertation</id>
  <updated>2015-11-23T00:00:00-00:00</updated>
  <published>2015-11-23T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  
  <author>
    <name>Nicola du Toit</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>nicoladutoit@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I have a lot of smart friends and family. I am surrounded by Masters and Doctors in assorted fields, and know several Doctors-to-be. The subject of dissertation writing comes up a lot, because many people I know have either survived the process by the skin of their teeth, or are struggling to get through it now. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back in November 2013, for my own M.Phil, I had an awful lot of dissertation to write. I treated my thesis like it was work, project managed the crap out of it, and remarkably got it done before my submission deadline. I churned out a first draft in record time, despite having a full time job and only being able to work on it at night. I’d like to share a few tips here which I reckon saved my bacon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;write-in-the-cloud&quot;&gt;1. Write in the cloud&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;col-md-3 image right&quot;&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/a/ad/Logo_of_Google_Drive.svg/600px-Logo_of_Google_Drive.svg.png&quot; height=&quot;100&quot; width=&quot;100&quot; alt=&quot;Google Drive logo&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use Google Docs! In 2015 if you are not writing your thesis in the cloud, you are quite simply a fool. Apologies if this sounds harsh, but we have incredible, versatile cloud storage and WYSIWYG editors available to us today - &lt;b&gt;use them!&lt;/b&gt; Google Docs is my personal favourite because you have epic backups and version control at all times. You can easily view your history of changes and go and recover that paragraph you deleted last week in a rage. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working like this brought me enormous peace of mind - I knew that my computer could burst into flames at any time and it would make absolutely no difference to my work because everything was automatically saved, synced and backed up to hell and gone!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Google Docs can also sync offline - this means that if you need to go and write your literature review on your iPad in a field, you can do so. When you’re done, don’t forget to quickly sync the offline doc by tethering to your phone. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Never&lt;/i&gt; rely on backing up to a hard drive. They fail. Don’t be that person who loses all their work the week before they’re due to submit. (&lt;a href=&quot;/articles/so-your-hard-drive-crashed/&quot;&gt;See my rant about this here&lt;/a&gt;). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And don’t worry about typesetting to begin with. Until you’re sitting with a final draft you don’t need to perfect your font choices and diagrams - you need to churn out words. Draft in Google Docs and typeset when you’re basically done proofreading. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;plan-all-the-things&quot;&gt;2. Plan all the things&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first step in managing any project is to plan your time. I created a Google spreadsheet which contained every day until my submission deadline. I then laid out all the chapters I had to write on a weekly basis, and all the sections within a chapter on a daily basis. I catered for weekends and nights off. I planned around Christmas holidays and New Year. While my schedule worked on days and weeks, there is no reason it wouldn’t work for weeks and months. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;col-md-5 image right&quot;&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/ThesisSpreadsheet.png&quot; data-lightbox=&quot;thesis&quot; title=&quot;The epic thesis triage spreadsheet&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/ThesisSpreadsheet.png&quot; alt=&quot;One Spreadsheet to rule them all&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;The spreadsheet of doom&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Work in the spreadsheet was colour coded - green for “done”, and yellow for “to do”. Important sub-deadlines were flagged in red. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I budgeted time for writing, editing and proofreading. And I allowed for iteration. This helped me avoid getting stuck on one thing for too long.  If I got to “section 1.4” on a certain day but had no inspiration I forced myself to write &lt;i&gt;something&lt;/i&gt;. Even if it was the most bare bones structure or a single idea, when I iterated back to that particular page I then had some words on the page. This did wonders for my writer’s block and really helped keep me afloat - instead of feeling overwhelmed by a huge and difficult task, I felt like I was always making progress, even if it was in small increments! &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My schedule was not cast in stone - it was absolutely a living document. I updated it every day and shuffled things around as the writing process evolved. There were obviously days when I was too tired to work, for example, and then I could easily shift things out, but it helped me see the longer term effect of moving things around. It wasn’t about enforcing work on myself, it was more about reducing the burden of having to remember what I was supposed to be working on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;create-routine&quot;&gt;3. Create routine&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A daily routine into which you can fit your research/writing is key. So for example, let every day start with coffee and a walk, or a trip to the gym. Then work 9am-12pm (with a break half way through), take a timeout for lunch, work 1-4pm, break for tea, and then do admin from 5-6pm… &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;col-md-5 image right&quot;&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/ThesisWine.jpg&quot; data-lightbox=&quot;thesis&quot; title=&quot;Thesis anaesthetic&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/ThesisWine.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A bottle of wine&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;It is acceptable to schedule wine into your daily routine.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll obviously know best what times of day you feel most productive and when it makes sense for you to work (for me I did my best work late at night, with a glass of wine). Figure this out, cater to your personal energy levels and take time out. Your brain won’t stop working on your research, even if you’re gardening or reading or going for a swim. This makes a huge difference to productivity. It’s much better than trying to impose a system which just doesn’t fit your daily rhythms!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Include exercise and plenty of sleep in your routine. Our bodies and brains do best when we have regular bed times and get more than 7 hours of sleep a night. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;clear-out-the-clutter&quot;&gt;4. Clear out the clutter&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make a tidy, calm and pleasant workspace for yourself. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Make a list of nice coffee shops nearby that have Wi-fi, for the days you need to get out of the house.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Use software like Evernote to organise your life. I kept all the papers I read stored as PDFs in Evernote. This meant I could access them anytime (because Evernote will sync to all your devices) and also tag them by author, topic, keyword etc. This made searching for particular stuff later on really easy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;dont-be-too-hard-on-yourself&quot;&gt;5. Don’t be too hard on yourself&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Writing a dissertation sucks. Research is bloody hard work. You will have good days and bad. Listen to your body, take breaks when you need to, and give credit where it’s due. You have to acknowledge the small things. Some days it will be impossible to sit and write for hours on end. But if you can read a couple of papers instead - bravo! All progress is good progress. Just get something useful done every day, no matter how small. And acknolwedge that it’s still a huge step in the right direction, even if it’s not exactly what you had planned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If, after all of this, you still find yourself feeling miserable and unmotivated all of the time, please &lt;b&gt;seek professional advice&lt;/b&gt; from your GP or therapist. Postgraduate studies are notoriously linked to depression and anxiety disorders. This is a very real thing that academics and supervisors often ignore. Believe it or not, your dissertation actually shouldn’t make you want to die. If you’re struggling to cope, you are not alone and you can and should get help. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This too shall pass. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;col-md-12 image center&quot;&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/PhDComic.gif&quot; data-lightbox=&quot;thesis&quot; title=&quot;PhD Comics&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/PhDComic.gif&quot; alt=&quot;PhD Comics&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;So true it hurts... &lt;br /&gt;By the venerable &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.phdcomics.com/&quot;&gt;PhD Comics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/articles/how-to-survive-a-dissertation&quot;&gt;How to survive a dissertation&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Nicola du Toit at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Nicola du Toit&lt;/a&gt; on November 23, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[So you want to be a UX designer...]]></title>
  <link>/articles/so-you-want-to-be-a-ux-designer</link>
  <id>/articles/so-you-want-to-be-a-ux-designer</id>
  <updated>2015-07-10T00:00:00-00:00</updated>
  <published>2015-07-10T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  
  <author>
    <name>Nicola du Toit</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>nicoladutoit@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;An acquaintance of mine recently put me in touch with a friend of theirs who was hoping to move into the (wonderful) world of UX design here in South Africa. She was working as a developer, and had done some formal but short UX training but was coming up against the age old issue of “where is your portfolio?”. The following is an adaptation of my advice to her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;make-a-portfolio-no-matter-what&quot;&gt;Make a portfolio, no matter what&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you can’t wangle any UX into your current work, then work on creating a portfolio in your spare time. This can consist of ideas that you evolve from concept to hi-fi mockups or, if you can code, into functioning prototypes that can live on the web. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A portfolio demonstrating a couple of ideas that you conceptualised, prototyped with users (read: family and friends!), tested and built into a hi-fidelity mockup will put you way ahead on the curve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;document-everything&quot;&gt;Document everything&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The purpose of a UX portfolio is to show that you understand and can apply user-centred methodologies and tools. Yes, the final product should be included, but it’s equally important to document &lt;i&gt;how&lt;/i&gt; you built that product. It’s like a high school maths problem: “show your ways of working!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;col-md-4 image right&quot;&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/coffee.jpg&quot; data-lightbox=&quot;ux-tips&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/coffee.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Coffee&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t be scared to include rough or messy work. For example, if you start designing wireframes on a paper napkin in a coffee shop, take a photo and explain how this was where your great idea was born! If you hold an informal focus group, document the questions you asked and write up your findings. It’s as important to show how you did your research and design, as it is to show the results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re not sure about which design steps to include, do some reading about the user-centred design (UCD) framework. UCD is the toolkit we use to design great user experiences. Contextual inquiries, participatory design/prototyping, usability testing - that’s all part of UCD! An excellent book about what tools to use when is &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.id-book.com/&quot;&gt;“Interaction Design” by Rogers, Sharp &amp;amp; Preece&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;learn-the-software&quot;&gt;Learn the software&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Almost every UX position I’ve seen advertised requires that you know &lt;a href=&quot;https://balsamiq.com&quot;&gt;Balsamiq&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.uxpin.com&quot;&gt;UXPin&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.axure.com&quot;&gt;Axure&lt;/a&gt;. All three have free trials and affordable licensing options. I would suggest you play with them all and then choose one and get to know it properly. Not only will you be able to produce shiny wireframes and mockups but you’ll also have an opinion on which design software you like best and why! &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other staple to be familiar with is Adobe CC. It can’t hurt to know your way around Photoshop and Illustrator. Adobe’s new cloud pricing structure is far more affordable than it used to be. And if you can’t afford Adobe products, then learn to use &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gimp.org&quot;&gt;GIMP&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://inkscape.org/en/&quot;&gt;Inkscape&lt;/a&gt; - two excellent and free alternatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;read-read-and-read-some-more&quot;&gt;Read, read and read some more&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col-md-4 image left&quot;&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/tweeps.jpg&quot; data-lightbox=&quot;ux-tips&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/tweeps.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Twitter is a great networking tool&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Tweet all the things! &lt;br /&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/mkhmarketing/8477893426&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Image by  mkhmarketing on Flickr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is an epic UX community on Twitter. For starters check out these tweeps: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.creativebloq.com/web-design/20-ux-twitter-accounts-you-should-follow-912782&quot;&gt;“20 UX Twitter Accounts You Should Follow”&lt;/a&gt;. They are always posting interesting articles and links. Read the links that they share and engage with them and their content! &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then, of course, Google is your friend. There is a huge amount of fantastic UX literature out there. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.usabilitycounts.com/2012/08/10/the-usability-counts-ux-resume-template-and-career-guide/&quot;&gt;Usability Counts’ “UX Resume and Career Guide”&lt;/a&gt; is a really good place to start if you’re new to UX. Also check out the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nngroup.com/&quot;&gt;Nielsen Norman Group&lt;/a&gt; website (started by the godfathers of UX). They have an awesome weekly newsletter, amongst other things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;if-you-have-the-time-study&quot;&gt;If you have the time: study!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are amazing formal and informal ways to study UX. Investigate what your local university offers. The University of Cape Town offers a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cs.uct.ac.za/mit/about.html&quot;&gt;Masters in Information Technology&lt;/a&gt; that includes Human-Computer Interaction. This is an excellent degree. For a faster learning experience, checkout UCT’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.getsmarter.co.za/courses/user-experience-design-short-course&quot;&gt;GetSmarter online UX course&lt;/a&gt;. And of course there are amazing free options online such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coursera.org/specialization/humancomputerinteraction/28?utm_medium=catalog&quot;&gt;Coursera’s HCI specialisation&lt;/a&gt;. If you’re flush with cash, definitely investigate &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.humanfactors.com/training/&quot;&gt;Human Factors International’s training programs&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;create-an-online-presence&quot;&gt;Create an online presence&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you haven’t already done so, build yourself a professional website. If you aren’t familiar with HTML and CSS there are free website options out there, but learning some basic markup will help you design for the web, and it looks good on your CV so it’s worth doing! (Check out &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.codecademy.com&quot;&gt;Codecademy&lt;/a&gt; if you’re not sure where to start). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;col-md-4 image right&quot;&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/thematrix.jpg&quot; data-lightbox=&quot;ux-tips&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/thematrix.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Red or blue?&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;(&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/tt2times/2568645910&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Image by Tony Werman on Flickr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Put your portfolio online. Keep it up to date. Blog, tweet, share. Online communication is important in the world of UX. If you can post or re-share a couple or articles a month, it’ll demonstrate that you’re always learning, interested and engaged. Employers love this! (And they will stalk you online before that interview!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;network&quot;&gt;Network&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Go to meetups! Go to conferences! Get to know who your local UX practitioners are and connect with them - have that cup of coffee! In Cape Town we have fairly regular &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.meetup.com/UX-Masterclass-Cape-Town/&quot;&gt;UX Masterclasses&lt;/a&gt;. These are a great way to meet people in the field. Attend the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.uxsouthafrica.com&quot;&gt;UX South Africa&lt;/a&gt; conference and workshops to learn and be inspired.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;have-faith&quot;&gt;Have faith&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You will find an awesome UX position but it may take time. In South Africa it’s still a fairly young field - a lot of companies are realising that they need UX but they aren’t sure why just yet. Keep looking and keep applying for positions. But be picky about what you apply for. Don’t go for the “UX/UI/graphic design/developer” job ads - those employers don’t know what they need from the role. In the meantime, keep working on your portfolio. You don’t have to be employed as a UX designer to start practising to be one. There’s no shame in saying “well I couldn’t do any UX in my current job, so I did all this in my spare time” - that says a helluva lot about you as a person and about your keenness to get into UX!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;col-md-12 image center&quot;&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/uxunicorn.jpg&quot; data-lightbox=&quot;ux-unicorn&quot; title=&quot;UX Unicorns!&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/uxunicorn.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Gun-toting cat riding a unicorn&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;A gun-toting cat riding a unicorn. Image possibly by &lt;a href=&quot;http://imgur.com/gallery/atz81&quot;&gt;oedaux on imgur&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;br /&gt; For more information about UX unicorns see &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.uie.com/articles/becoming_a_unicorn/&quot;&gt;Jared Spool&#39;s article&lt;/a&gt; on the subject!&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/articles/so-you-want-to-be-a-ux-designer&quot;&gt;So you want to be a UX designer...&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Nicola du Toit at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Nicola du Toit&lt;/a&gt; on July 10, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Sketchnoting UX Jhb 2015]]></title>
  <link>/articles/sketchnoting-uxjhb-2015</link>
  <id>/articles/sketchnoting-uxjhb-2015</id>
  <updated>2015-05-20T00:00:00-00:00</updated>
  <published>2015-05-20T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  
  <author>
    <name>Nicola du Toit</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>nicoladutoit@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;col-md-4 col-xs-6 image right&quot;&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/joburg.jpg&quot; data-lightbox=&quot;joburg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/joburg.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Johannesburg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The Big Smoke&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In October 2014 I had the pleasure of attending South Africa’s first UX conference in Cape Town. Armed with my iPad and offline Google Docs, I took pages and pages of notes. I promised myself I would share them, go back to them, write blog posts about them. And of course I haven’t touched those documents again. Last week I headed up to Johannesburg for #UXJhb2015. Instead of taking boring text notes, this time I decided to try my hand at sketchnoting in the hope that it would produce more useful and visually appealling notes that I may actually refer to again at least once in my life…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;so-what-is-sketchnoting-anyway&quot;&gt;So what is sketchnoting anyway?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sketchnoting is simply visual note taking. Instead of just writing down words, you draw images, patterns or shapes that relate to those words. The beauty of sketchnoting is that it requires no advanced drawing skills. As long as you have some cool stationary and you can draw some basic shapes, you’re good to go. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Internet is awash with great resources for how to get started including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://rohdesign.com/&quot;&gt;Mike Rohde’s site (and his books)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Smashing Mag’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.smashingmagazine.com/2014/11/10/how-to-get-started-with-sketchnotes/&quot;&gt;“How to get started with sketchnotes”&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;UX Mastery’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://uxmastery.com/sketchnoting-101-how-to-create-awesome-visual-notes/&quot;&gt;“Sketchnoting 101”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;taking-the-plunge&quot;&gt;Taking the plunge&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although I initially felt a bit uncertain and intimidated by the idea of drawing again, after the first talk I was completely sold. I found that sketchnoting is a far more engaging way to listen to great speakers - it felt as if by writing &lt;i&gt;and&lt;/i&gt; drawing, my brain was able to process information more efficiently, more thoroughly and with far less effort. My sketchnotes evolved as I got more comfortable with the process (and paid less attention to my shitty inner art critic), and it was interesting to watch my creativity wax and wane depending on my energy levels and the pace of each talk. I also found myself feeling far less mentally drained than usual at the end of each day. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall I feel like my experiment was a great success. I remember far more of what I learned at the conference, and a whole talk comes back to me with a quick glance at my notes - it’s as if I can remeber the entire experience of each talk, not just fragments, because I was present in an engaged and creative way. I’ll definitely be attempting this in future and can highly recommend it as a fresh and fun way to take meaningful notes during meetings, talks or workshops.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;col-md-4&quot;&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/Sketchnotes/EricSchaffer1.png&quot; data-lightbox=&quot;sketchnotes&quot; title=&quot;Eric Schaffer pg 1&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/Sketchnotes/EricSchaffer1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Eric Schaffer&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;col-md-4&quot;&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/Sketchnotes/EricSchaffer2.png&quot; data-lightbox=&quot;sketchnotes&quot; title=&quot;Eric Schaffer pg 2&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images//Sketchnotes/EricSchaffer2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Eric Schaffer&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;

    &lt;div class=&quot;col-md-4&quot;&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/Sketchnotes/HobbsFenn.png&quot; data-lightbox=&quot;sketchnotes&quot; title=&quot;Jason Hobbs and Terrence Fenn&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images//Sketchnotes/HobbsFenn.png&quot; alt=&quot;Jason Hobbs and Terence Fenn&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;col-md-4&quot;&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/Sketchnotes/KariPeters.png&quot; data-lightbox=&quot;sketchnotes&quot; title=&quot;Kari Peters&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images//Sketchnotes/KariPeters.png&quot; alt=&quot;Kari Peters&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;col-md-4&quot;&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/Sketchnotes/PhilBarrett.png&quot; data-lightbox=&quot;sketchnotes&quot; title=&quot;Phil Barrett&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images//Sketchnotes/PhilBarrett.png&quot; alt=&quot;Phil Barrett&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;

    &lt;div class=&quot;col-md-4&quot;&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/Sketchnotes/NancyDouyon.png&quot; data-lightbox=&quot;sketchnotes&quot; title=&quot;Nancy Douyon&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images//Sketchnotes/NancyDouyon.png&quot; alt=&quot;Nancy Douyon&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;col-md-4&quot;&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/Sketchnotes/FaraiMadzuma.png&quot; data-lightbox=&quot;sketchnotes&quot; title=&quot;Farai Madzuma&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images//Sketchnotes/FaraiMadzuma.png&quot; alt=&quot;Farai Madzuma&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;col-md-4&quot;&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/Sketchnotes/AndrewBeckley.png&quot; data-lightbox=&quot;sketchnotes&quot; title=&quot;Andrew Beckley&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images//Sketchnotes/AndrewBeckley.png&quot; alt=&quot;Andrew Beckley&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;col-md-4&quot;&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/Sketchnotes/GarthBraithwaite.png&quot; data-lightbox=&quot;sketchnotes&quot; title=&quot;Garth Braithwaite&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images//Sketchnotes/GarthBraithwaite.png&quot; alt=&quot;Garth Braithwaite&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;col-md-4&quot;&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/Sketchnotes/RynoBooysens.png&quot; data-lightbox=&quot;sketchnotes&quot; title=&quot;Ryno Booysens&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images//Sketchnotes/RynoBooysens.png&quot; alt=&quot;Ryno Booysens&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;col-md-4&quot;&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/Sketchnotes/RobCowie.png&quot; data-lightbox=&quot;sketchnotes&quot; title=&quot;Rob Cowie&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images//Sketchnotes/RobCowie.png&quot; alt=&quot;Rob Cowie&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class=&quot;col-md-4&quot;&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/Sketchnotes/JoannaChao.png&quot; data-lightbox=&quot;sketchnotes&quot; title=&quot;Joanna Chao&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images//Sketchnotes/JoannaChao.png&quot; alt=&quot;JoannaChao&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/articles/sketchnoting-uxjhb-2015&quot;&gt;Sketchnoting UX Jhb 2015&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Nicola du Toit at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Nicola du Toit&lt;/a&gt; on May 20, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Google and mobile usability]]></title>
  <link>/articles/google-and-mobile-usability</link>
  <id>/articles/google-and-mobile-usability</id>
  <updated>2015-04-22T00:00:00-00:00</updated>
  <published>2015-04-22T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  
  <author>
    <name>Nicola du Toit</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>nicoladutoit@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Google &lt;a href=&quot;http://googlewebmastercentral.blogspot.de/2015/02/finding-more-mobile-friendly-search.html?mc_cid=cc21b18877&amp;amp;mc_eid=610a07c84b&quot;&gt;announced in February&lt;/a&gt; that as of this week mobile-friendliness will be a factor in their search algorithms. In other words, content and sites that are optimized for mobile phones will be given preference in Google’s search result listings. For those of us with responsive sites, this is wonderful news but according to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.smashingmagazine.com/smashing-newsletter-issue-135/?mc_cid=cc21b18877&amp;amp;mc_eid=610a07c84b&quot;&gt;Smashing Magazine&lt;/a&gt;, 25% of sites are not responsive. That’s a lot of internet to fix.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;col-md-5 col-xs-6 image left&quot;&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/videophone.jpg&quot; data-lightbox=&quot;videophone&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/videophone.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A Videophone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The videphone: before Facetime was cool.&lt;br /&gt;
(Image by &lt;a href=&quot;http://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Videophone_IMG_1107-white.jpg&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Rama&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;on Wikimedia Commons)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While it may leave some webmasters in the lurch, from a UX perspective this is an awesome move. Usability on mobile phones is fickle at the best of times but there are few things more frustrating than trying to find information on a site that is absolutely not intended to be viewed or used on a small screen. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Google is effectively incentivising website owners to evaluate their content and improve it for mobile users: such is the power of a good Google search ranking! &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To help us all out, Google has provided several useful tools to help people make the transition:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/webmasters/tools/mobile-friendly/?mc_cid=cc21b18877&amp;amp;mc_eid=610a07c84b&quot;&gt;The Mobile Friendly Test&lt;/a&gt; let’s you type in your site’s URL and hit “Analyze” to see what Googlebot thinks of your web-stuff; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/webmasters/tools/mobile-usability?utm_source=wmc-blog&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_campaign=mobile-friendly&amp;amp;pli=1&quot;&gt;Webmaster Tools &amp;amp; The Mobile Usability Report&lt;/a&gt; which gives great feedback on specific usability issues with your site; and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://developers.google.com/webmasters/mobile-sites/get-started/?utm_source=wmc-blog&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_campaign=mobile-friendly&quot;&gt;A comprehensive guide&lt;/a&gt; to designing mobile-friendly websites. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;col-md-4 col-xs-6 image right&quot;&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/googlebot.png&quot; data-lightbox=&quot;googlebot&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/googlebot.png&quot; alt=&quot;The Googlebot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;That&#39;s Mr Googlebot to you.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier this year I received a pretty stern email from Google Webmaster Tools regarding one of the websites I maintain:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Google systems have tested 12 pages from your site and found that 100% of them have critical mobile usability errors. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This prompted me to take action and haul a bunch of appalling MSFrontpage HTML kicking and screaming into into the 21st century (actually I just deleted it all and started over - more on this in another blog post). But a second site I built years ago (before Bootstrap was a thing) now requires some urgent TLC. Off to the CSS drawing board I go!&lt;/p&gt;


  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/articles/google-and-mobile-usability&quot;&gt;Google and mobile usability&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Nicola du Toit at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Nicola du Toit&lt;/a&gt; on April 22, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[The heat death of a blog]]></title>
  <link>/articles/the-heat-death-of-a-blog</link>
  <id>/articles/the-heat-death-of-a-blog</id>
  <updated>2015-04-16T00:00:00-00:00</updated>
  <published>2015-04-16T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  
  <author>
    <name>Nicola du Toit</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>nicoladutoit@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Much to my horror, this blog has been dormant for months. I inadvertently did “one of those” - a nice rush of content up front and then nothing for ages because life got the better of me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not going to write a long and self-indulgent post about all the reasons why I’ve been to busy to blog but I will say this much: I started out writing a series of rather long posts. And that got me stuck in a bit of a rut where I’d think “ooh I have this great idea but no time to turn it into a 1000 word piece”. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve realised recently that writing short pieces, but writing more regularly is probably a better strategy. Much like an agile user-centred design process breaks up an enormous task into smaller bite-size chunks and iterates, blogging often and more briefly about particular ideas is a fresh approach which I’d like to try this year…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sheryl_Sandberg&quot;&gt;Sheryl Sandberg&lt;/a&gt; quote goes: “done is better than perfect”.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/articles/the-heat-death-of-a-blog&quot;&gt;The heat death of a blog&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Nicola du Toit at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Nicola du Toit&lt;/a&gt; on April 16, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[The UX design process]]></title>
  <link>/articles/the-ux-design-process</link>
  <id>/articles/the-ux-design-process</id>
  <updated>2014-01-28T00:00:00-00:00</updated>
  <published>2014-01-28T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  
  <author>
    <name>Nicola du Toit</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>nicoladutoit@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;There are many ways in which one can do design work. The usual process I follow in my current workplace is outlined here. Although I am a firm believer in a user-centred process, due to external time and financial constraints, some recent projects have included far less usability testing and market research than I would have liked. Different projects for different clients and teams require different approaches, but user requirements should always come first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Research&lt;/b&gt;: every project starts with research, be it into users, a brand, design guidelines and patterns, related products or all of the above. Before I draw a single sketch, I like to have an overview of who my users are, what they need to do, and how they should be able to do it. The result of this work is usually copious notes, use cases, workflows and a few possible site structures. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Ideate&lt;/b&gt;: once I have a clearer sense of my users and the scope of the project, I hit my notebook to brainstorm, sketch, doodle and think. I experiment with different ideas, iterating rapidly to do a creative dump of all the thoughts, chaotic notes and design options in my mind. I am usually able to narrow a new design down to one or two possibilities which will form the backbone of the project, in which case it’s time to start prototyping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Design&lt;/b&gt;: the official design process usually starts with paper prototypes that are the result of my initial brainstorming. Once a design starts taking shape on paper, I’ll couple it with sitemaps, wireframes and moodboards, to start putting flesh onto the project’s bare bones. I use different software depending on the fidelity of the mockups required. Sometimes hand drawn sketches suffice, but more often than not I land up working in Balsamiq, Inkscape or Photoshop because a picture really is worth a thousand words.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Brainstorming&lt;/b&gt;: once I have mockups in the bag, it’s time to sit down with my client (usually my employers and colleagues) and present my ideas. While it can be gruelling having a new design analysed and criticised, group discussions with team members and all involved parties provide invaluable insight and feedback. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Refinement&lt;/b&gt;: input from group sessions is used to improve the design, which usually requires some tweaking and editing. Improvements and further feedback usually occur in a number of iterations until everyone is happy with the final design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Final specification&lt;/b&gt;: much of the design work I currently do gets outsourced to external developers. If this is the case, depending on the project, the final brief will usually include a detailed technical specification, high-fidelity mockups, sitemaps and any other relevant technical or creative material that could be of use. Once everything has been collated it gets sent off to our developers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Development and testing&lt;/b&gt;: whether development happens in-house or externally the implementation phase typically involves many iterations of development, further changes to design, and thorough testing. At all stages of the design process, progress is cyclical and work needs to be continually revisited and reassessed!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;col-md-6 image center&quot;&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/post-it.jpg&quot; data-lightbox=&quot;post-its&quot; title=&quot;Brainstorming use cases and functionality&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/post-it.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;mapping site functionality with post-it notes&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/articles/the-ux-design-process&quot;&gt;The UX design process&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Nicola du Toit at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Nicola du Toit&lt;/a&gt; on January 28, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tips for installing Jekyll with So Simple and Jekyll Slideshow]]></title>
  <link>/articles/tips-for-installing-jekyll-with-so-simple-and-jekyll-slideshow</link>
  <id>/articles/tips-for-installing-jekyll-with-so-simple-and-jekyll-slideshow</id>
  <updated>2014-01-16T00:00:00-00:00</updated>
  <published>2014-01-16T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  
  <author>
    <name>Nicola du Toit</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>nicoladutoit@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://jekyllrb.com/&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt; is my new favourite thing. I used it to build this site and most excitingly it integrates seamlessly with &lt;a href=&quot;http://github.com&quot;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;. There are a number of shiny themes available for Jekyll. This site uses the &lt;a href=&quot;http://mademistakes.com/articles/so-simple-jekyll-theme/&quot;&gt;So Simple Theme&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The processes for &lt;a href=&quot;http://jekyllrb.com/docs/installation/&quot;&gt;installing Jekyll&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mmistakes/so-simple-theme/&quot;&gt;installing this theme&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://help.github.com/articles/using-jekyll-with-pages&quot;&gt;using Jekyll with GitHub Pages&lt;/a&gt; are well documented and mostly simple, but I did run into a few weird errors when I added the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/matthewowen/jekyll-slideshow&quot;&gt;Jekyll Slideshow&lt;/a&gt; gallery plugin to my installation - I think due to version conflicts between all the different bits of software.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I managed to debug the process on my home laptop, then tried running Jekyll on my work machine and ran into the same problem. Stupidly, I couldn’t remember what the hell I’d done to fix it in the first place. For my own future reference and for your edification and delight, here is a list of commands that should install Jekyll, (Ruby and RubyGems), the So Simple theme and the Jekyll Slideshow plugin. These instructions should work for Ubuntu 12.04 and 13.10.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To install Jekyll you’ll first need to install Ruby and RubyGems:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo apt-get install ruby1.9.3
sudo apt-get install gem
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For good measure install the following Ruby extensions too:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo apt-get install libreadline-ruby1.9 libruby1.9 libopenssl-ruby
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then use RubyGems to install Jekyll:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo gem install jekyll
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once this is done, &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mmistakes/so-simple-theme/fork&quot;&gt;fork&lt;/a&gt; and clone the So Simple theme repo and follow the instructions &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mmistakes/so-simple-theme/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to customise and set up your new site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instructions for getting the Jekyll Slideshow plugin into your own repo are available &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/matthewowen/jekyll-slideshow&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. (Assuming you’re already using plugins, you’ll just need to copy across the &lt;code&gt;_plugins&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;jesl&lt;/code&gt; folders into your projects, and call some additional CSS.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jekyll Slideshow uses ImageMagick as well as the RMagick and nokogiri gems however, and this is where things started getting hairy for me but theoretically it should work if you’ve got the latest versions of everything on your machine. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ImageMagick is probably already installed if you’re in Ubuntu. To check:
    convert -version&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If it isn’t installed:
    sudo apt-get install imagemagick&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While you’re at it, also install the following library:
    sudo apt-get install libmagickwand-dev &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Assuming you’ve already copied the necessary bits of Jekyll Slideshow into your repo, you’ll need to install this plugins required gems:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo gem install rmagick
sudo gem install nokogiri
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Theoretically this should work. If it doesn’t, you might also want to try:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo apt-get install libxslt-dev libxml2-dev
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should now be able to build and serve up your Jekyll site (with a functional theme and plugin) using the &lt;a href=&quot;http://jekyllrb.com/docs/usage/&quot;&gt;standard Jekyll commands&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To integrate your new Jekyll repo with GitHub, you’ll also need to install Bundler:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo gem install bundler
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After this, create a file in your repo called &lt;code&gt;Gemfile&lt;/code&gt; and add the line &lt;code&gt;gem &#39;github-pages&#39;&lt;/code&gt;. Then run the command:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;bundle install.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suspect there may be an overlap between Bundler and the other gems I’ve installed, but following this process was the only way I could get everything to work, error free. &lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/articles/tips-for-installing-jekyll-with-so-simple-and-jekyll-slideshow&quot;&gt;Tips for installing Jekyll with So Simple and Jekyll Slideshow&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Nicola du Toit at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Nicola du Toit&lt;/a&gt; on January 16, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why I love the Gautrain]]></title>
  <link>/articles/why-i-love-the-gautrain</link>
  <id>/articles/why-i-love-the-gautrain</id>
  <updated>2013-09-17T00:00:00-00:00</updated>
  <published>2013-11-14T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  
  <author>
    <name>Nicola du Toit</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>nicoladutoit@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I was 29 years old the first time I rode on a train in my hometown, &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Johannesburg&quot;&gt;Johannesburg&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To many people, this might sound like a strange fact, but white kids like me who grew up in the Southern end of the Northern ‘burbs in the 1980’s and 90’s didn’t take trains or buses or taxis. Public transport, where available, was notoriously complicated, unreliable and often just not safe. Why would you use it if your parents both had cars and were (mostly) willing to spend hours of their lives driving you around?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst there have always been trains going into Joburg and around Joburg, there have never been trains forming a network inside Joburg; trains that could get me to places I needed to be (in my Northern suburbs bubble); trains that could easily replace a parental vehicle. Joburg does not have century-old subterranean veins like London or Berlin or New York.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;col-md-6 image center&quot;&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/London_Underground_circa_1900.jpg&quot; data-lightbox=&quot;underground&quot;&gt;&lt;img border=&quot;0&quot; src=&quot;/images/London_Underground_circa_1900.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The London Underground in 1890&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Trains under the ground: not a thing in 1890&#39;s Joburg.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so, I grew up believing that trains were really a thing that only happened in England and Europe and the rest of the First World. I traveled on trains in London, Paris, Rome, Berlin, Singapore and California, before I stepped onto one in the city I have lived longest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I doubt very much that I will ever forget my first &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gautrain&quot;&gt;Gautrain&lt;/a&gt; trip from Sandton to O.R. Thambo airport. I was in Joburg for work - a 36 hour whirlwind trip - and by the time my mum had dropped me off at the station, I was tired and stressed out. She assured me that the ticket machines were really easy to use, but I knew I had to get a Gold Card (like London’s Oyster card) and preload it with the correct amount of money, then find the right platform, get on the right train and so on and so forth. This I have done countless times in foreign languages, in strange cities, in the dead of night, and here I was doing it for the first time in my home city, more nervous, clueless and overwhelmed than I’d ever been overseas, probably because I had no idea what to expect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Card and ticket bought, I was stunned by how user-friendly the machines were (mother is always right!). Things were looking up. I swiped my way through the turnstiles and then began the long escalator descent to Platform C, nine (!) floors underground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe I was on the 3rd long and steep, Tube-like escalator when I heard that unmistakable train-whooshing-in-a-tunnel sound. It was completely surreal. A First World, European noise in a mad, gritty African city! London in Johannesburg - how completely bizarre!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The train journey itself seemed like a dream - cutting over highways and intersections that I knew so well. Clean, safe and so fast! Fifteen minutes from Sandton to the airport?! This was the stuff of Joburg dreams when I was growing up! I believe I sent an inarticulate SMS to my mum saying something along the lines of “&lt;i&gt;Wheeeeeeeeeeeee!!!!!! Hehehe&lt;/i&gt;”. At the Ortia station, I walked straight into the airport feeling like I was in San Francisco again. I met my boss shortly afterwards and told him that I felt like a kid at Christmas. It was honestly one of the most exciting, exhilarating experiences I’d had all year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The novelty of taking a high speed train in my own city, in my own country! The novelty of safe, efficient public transport not only replacing a road trip, but shortening the commute to the Airport to a fraction of the time, not to mention the stress! The novelty of taking just a few minutes to travel dozens of kilometres during peak rush hour traffic! All of this excitement I put down to Gautrain-virgin glee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;col-md-6 image center&quot;&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://farm1.staticflickr.com/250/520316324_cdc8283982_z.jpg&quot; data-lightbox=&quot;jozi&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://farm1.staticflickr.com/250/520316324_cdc8283982_z.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Joburg traffic&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Joburg at rush hour: less appealing than triple bypass surgery.&lt;br /&gt;
Image by &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.flickr.com/photos/francapicc/&quot;&gt;jespahjoy&lt;/a&gt; on Flickr&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until yesterday, when (several months later) I caught the Gautrain to the airport and rode on a Joburg train for the second time in my entire life. And hearing that amazing train-whooshing-in-a-tunnel sound, again brought a lump to my throat and tears to my eyes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I realised yesterday that it is not a European or American noise, curiously displaced in an African city. It is not a London-in-Joburg sound. It is a Joburg-in-Joburg sound. It is the incredible sound of a country shifting gears and cruising along into the First World. It the sound of progress, burrowing away through the South African soil. Those tunnels smell of hope and progress and prosperity. The Gautrain is quite simply a symbol of South African future potential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;col-md-6 image center&quot;&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/gautrain.jpg&quot; data-lightbox=&quot;gautrain&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/gautrain.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The Gautrain, Ortia Station&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;21st century Joburg is a pretty shiny sight. &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my lifetime I have often wondered what this magnificent country would be like today if we didn’t have an appalling history of oppression and bigotry; if all South Africans had been permitted to realise their full potential for the last four centuries; and if democracy and capitalism had been the norm for hundreds of years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because we can’t undo history, I have also often wondered what future South Africa will be like. What will it be like to have efficient, affordable public transport for all? What will it be like when all of our citizens have homes and teachers and books and jobs? What will this country of Acacias and dust-rolling hills and smiles and dry bones and weathered hands feel like when it’s managed to heal its wounds?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Catching the Gautrain today, I realised that we are already watching the sun rise on those rolling green hills. Whilst the past and much of the present is still painful and complicated and difficult to fix, future South Africa is already here. It’s happening now, one train trip at a time, literally in the rich red soil beneath our feet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;col-md-6 image center&quot;&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8318/8023986234_5d22064db6_c.jpg&quot; data-lightbox=&quot;mountains&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8318/8023986234_5d22064db6_c.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Image by  &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.flickr.com/photos/wildlife_encounters/&quot; alt=&quot;Rolling green hills&quot;&gt;Steve Slater (Wildlife Encounters)&lt;/a&gt; on Flickr&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/articles/why-i-love-the-gautrain&quot;&gt;Why I love the Gautrain&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Nicola du Toit at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Nicola du Toit&lt;/a&gt; on November 14, 2013.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[ZoneAlarm you're dead to me now]]></title>
  <link>/articles/zonealarm-youre-dead-to-me-now</link>
  <id>/articles/zonealarm-youre-dead-to-me-now</id>
  <updated>2013-08-14T00:00:00-00:00</updated>
  <published>2013-08-14T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  
  <author>
    <name>Nicola du Toit</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>nicoladutoit@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Having used &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.zonealarm.com/security/en-us/home.htm&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;ZoneAlarm&lt;/a&gt;’s free firewall in Windows for years and years, I just tried to upgrade, and got this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;col-md-10 image center&quot;&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;/images/zonealarm.PNG&quot; data-lightbox=&quot;zonealarm&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/zonealarm.PNG&quot; alt=&quot;ZoneAlarm dark patterns&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“To enable “Agree” please check the two boxes below.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Set ZoneAlarm search as my home page and new tab for: All Browsers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Set ZoneAlarm Search as my default search provider for: All Browsers.&quot;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cheers ZoneAlarm. It’s been real.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would love to know how many users you’re going to lose thanks to your new policy of entrapment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Update: on uninstalling the damn thing, I was asked to provide customer feedback, so I did: “Remove the checkboxes, and I’ll reinstall your product.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/articles/zonealarm-youre-dead-to-me-now&quot;&gt;ZoneAlarm you're dead to me now&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Nicola du Toit at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Nicola du Toit&lt;/a&gt; on August 14, 2013.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[So your hard drive crashed...]]></title>
  <link>/articles/so-your-hard-drive-crashed</link>
  <id>/articles/so-your-hard-drive-crashed</id>
  <updated>2013-02-06T00:00:00-00:00</updated>
  <published>2013-08-14T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  
  <author>
    <name>Nicola du Toit</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>nicoladutoit@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In the last couple of months I’ve had to listen to a number of friends and colleagues lamenting the recently-occured, or impending crash of their hard drive/flash disk/computer, resulting in a catastrophic loss of data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have two, highly unsympathetic words for them: &lt;b&gt;cloud storage&lt;/b&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;col-md-4 col-xs-6 image right&quot;&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5094/5472536812_c2dd4e93f6.jpg&quot; data-lightbox=&quot;drive&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5094/5472536812_c2dd4e93f6.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A hard drive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&quot;I&#39;m in your laptop. Flipping all your bits.&quot;&lt;br /&gt;
(Image by &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.flickr.com/photos/walkn/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;walknboston&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;on Flickr)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this day and age it is unbelievably easy to back up data. And not in the “copy it onto my five external drives and a DVD” sense of the word. I’m talking about syncing things into cyberspace, or, better still, actually creating them in cyberspace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hardware is fickle. &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bit_rot&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Bit rot&lt;/a&gt; is a bitch. As are &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cosmic_rays&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;cosmic rays&lt;/a&gt;.
Basically, any combination of silicon and solder ultimately results in failure, panic and tears.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this blog post is not about the untrustworthy nature of hardware. It’s about &lt;b&gt;why you should no longer care&lt;/b&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a stack of gleaming, cumulonimbus clouds out there in cyberspace which can and will save your bacon and your files. In no particular order, I give you the five current rockstars of online file storage and synchronization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://drive.google.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;1. Google Drive &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;col-md-3 image&quot;&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/a/ad/Logo_of_Google_Drive.svg/600px-Logo_of_Google_Drive.svg.png&quot; height=&quot;100&quot; width=&quot;100&quot; alt=&quot;Google Drive logo&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine a world in which Microsoft Office was free. A world in which you could make documents online, view them, edit them, have them automatically saved. Imagine being able to use version control on those documents - to roll back to earlier versions, or review your history. Now, imagine being able to access those documents on any one of your devices. And, just in case this wasn’t idyllic enough: imagine being able to share them with other people, who can then comment, edit, collaborate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enter the ninja: Google Drive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyone with a Google account has access to Google Drive. You get 15GB of storage for free (that’s a shit tonne of Word files, trust me) with the option to upgrade to 100GB for a whopping $4.99 per month. You never, &lt;b&gt;ever&lt;/b&gt; have to save a document again, and you never have to lose one either. Your docs will sync on basically any device (most of which let you edit too), and best of all, you can share them, let people comment on them, and author collaboratively and remotely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;col-md-5 right image&quot;&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://farm2.staticflickr.com/1191/543334336_dc24ebe65e_z.jpg&quot; data-lightbox=&quot;cloud&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://farm2.staticflickr.com/1191/543334336_dc24ebe65e_z.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Storm clouds&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Why hit Ctrl+S when you can write in the sky?&lt;br /&gt;
(&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.flickr.com/photos/nicholas_t/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Image by  Nicholas_T on Flickr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To give you one extreme use case: there’s a small start-up in Cape Town who &lt;b&gt;use Google Drive to author school textbooks&lt;/b&gt;. That’s right folks: they author entire textbooks using Google Drive. Documents are automatically saved. They are shared with multiple authors, who work remotely and can write, comment, collaborate and edit in the same document.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;2. GitHub&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;col-md-3 image right&quot;&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.global.ssl.fastly.net/images/modules/logos_page/Octocat.png&quot; width=&quot;200&quot; alt=&quot;GitHub logo&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Octocat is in your repo&lt;/a&gt;, watching all your things.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Github&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;: “GitHub is a web-based hosting service for software development projects that use the Git revision control system”. Git (the rock upon which GitHub is built) is revision control software, built by none other than &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Linus_Torvalds&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Linus Torvalds&lt;/a&gt; (of Linux kernel fame). GitHub is basically the king of version control. If you have a bunch of people working on the same files at the same time, this bad boy will keep track of all those changes, and merge them appropriately. Like most sensible cloud services, they offer free and paid versions too, depending on your privacy and size requirements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can roll back repositories, clone them, merge them, fork them… You can create, assign and track issues. You can view stunning visualizations of who’s changed what, where and when…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short: Linus Torvalds and the GitHub team deserve a repository-shaped cake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dropbox.com/&quot;&gt;3. Dropbox&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col-md-3 image&quot;&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/dropbox-logos_dropbox-vertical-blue.png&quot; alt=&quot;Dropbox logo&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those computer users who don’t trust Google, or don’t need the larny version control that GitHub has to offer, Dropbox is surely the most simple off-site storage solution. Dropbox gives you up to 18GB free (though friend referrals and social network sharing get you more data). After that, pricing starts at $10 per 100GB. Dropbox sits on your computer disguised as any other folder. And syncs the hell out of whatever happens in that folder. No need for backups, no need for tedious uploads. Dropbox will handle all of that for you. And, as with any well-synced data, you can access it from any device and from the web.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dropbox is ideal for lazy users, who, like me, want offsite syncing and backup that can babysit itself. I recently upgraded to a premium account and am syncing 75GB of photos. Because I like to sleep at night. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://evernote.com/&quot;&gt;4. Evernote&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col-md-4 col-xs-md-6 image&quot;&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/elephant.JPG&quot; data-lightbox=&quot;ellie&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/elephant.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;An elephant&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;A filing cabinet with ivory teeth.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Evernote is a brilliant tool for people who want to be organised. Content (in all shapes and sizes) can be organised into notebooks and folders, and labelled with tags. Imagine keeping track of a whack of PDF’s, web clippings and notes for a thesis literature review. Now imagine those same documents neatly filed and grouped, with searchable titles and tags. And now imagine all of this organisation being available to you on any device and on the web. Who needs a personal assistant when you have an elephant?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;col-md-3 image right&quot;&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://evernote.com/media/img/logos/evernote_logo_4c-sm.png&quot; alt=&quot;Evernote logo&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://evernote.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Evernote elephant&lt;/a&gt; has got you covered with his trunk.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Evernote also comes with a large suite of helper tools. The &lt;a href=&quot;http://evernote.com/webclipper/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Evernote web clipper&lt;/a&gt; is my favourite (for seamlessly saving bits of websites into my Evernote notebooks) but &lt;a href=&quot;http://evernote.com/skitch/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Skitch&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://evernote.com/penultimate/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Penultimate&lt;/a&gt; apparently come highly
recommended too. As with the other services, Evernote provides free access in exchange for (very reasonably) limited data, with premium, paid packages if you need more bandwidth. What’s not to love about this pachyderm?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.flickr.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;5. Flickr&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;col-md-4 image&quot;&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/7/78/Floppy_disc.jpg/794px-Floppy_disc.jpg&quot; data-lightbox=&quot;stiffy&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/7/78/Floppy_disc.jpg/794px-Floppy_disc.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A stiffy disk&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;You can store precisely no photos on one of these. (Image by&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:Floppy_disc.jpg&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Victor Korniyenko&lt;/a&gt; on WikiCommons)&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Up until fairly recently Flickr was cool for sharing photos, but in my books wouldn’t have merited a mention on a life-saving list like this. That was until they announced that anyone and everyone can now have &lt;b&gt;one free terabyte&lt;/b&gt; of storage on their site. That’s 1 000 000 000 000 bytes or 694 444 444 floppy disks (3/5 in 1.44 MB HD disks, to be precise). Flickr is the first site I know of to offer a tonne of free space like this, and hopefully, their new plan will put pressure on similar websites to do the same. (Dropbox, I’m looking at you!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike Dropbox, Flickr does not sync (i.e. you can upload only), and it’s only meant for photo and video sharing. But you can upload your digital media, neatly organised into sets, with tags and licensing, until the proverbial cows come home. Flickr displays your pics nicely as albums, and of course there’s a lot of community involved so you can easily share photos, write comments, join groups and so on. It takes some organisation and dedication to get set up but I know several people who are die-hard fans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This list is by no means meant to be exhaustive, but it is meant to be enlightening. There really is no excuse for data-loss related alcoholism and depression these days. As I type this, I am smug in the knowledge that my Masters’ dissertation and prototypes are tucked away in Google Drive (the writing bits), GitHub (the programming bits) and Evernote (the reading bits), and my photos are busily being uploaded into the Dropbox cyberspace, where they will be backed up on server after server and distributed into The Cloud.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;col-md-5 image center&quot;&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.google.com/about/datacenters/gallery/images/_2000/CBF_009.jpg&quot; data-lightbox=&quot;google&quot;&gt;&lt;img border=&quot;0&quot; src=&quot;http://www.google.com/about/datacenters/gallery/images/_2000/CBF_009.jpg&quot; lat=&quot;A Google data centre&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Not as portable as a USB hard drive but possibly more reliable.&lt;br /&gt;
(Image by&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.google.com/about/datacenters/gallery/#/tech/2&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Google&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/articles/so-your-hard-drive-crashed&quot;&gt;So your hard drive crashed...&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Nicola du Toit at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Nicola du Toit&lt;/a&gt; on August 14, 2013.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why CC-BY-SA should die]]></title>
  <link>/articles/why-cc-by-sa-should-die</link>
  <id>/articles/why-cc-by-sa-should-die</id>
  <updated>2013-02-06T00:00:00-00:00</updated>
  <published>2013-03-28T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  
  <author>
    <name>Nicola du Toit</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>nicoladutoit@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Creative commons copyright licenses are, in a nutshell, awesome. They offer flexibile, standardised, &lt;b&gt;open&lt;/b&gt;, alternatives to the miserable “ © All Rights Reserved” that is so prevalent in the world today. I’m not going to go into detail here about how copyright licenses are generally misused. I am, however, going to complain about how one particular open license is commonly used, and why that usage sucks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to creative commons (&lt;a href=&quot;http://creativecommons.org/licenses/&quot;&gt;http://creativecommons.org/licenses/&lt;/a&gt;), the Attribution-ShareAlike CC-BY-SA license:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;lets others remix, tweak, and build upon your work even for commercial 
purposes, as long as they credit you and license their new creations 
under the identical terms. This license is often compared to “copyleft” 
free and open source software licenses. All new works based on yours will carry the same license, so any derivatives will also allow commercial use. This is the license used by Wikipedia, and is recommended for materials that would benefit from incorporating content from Wikipedia and similarly licensed projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This sounds very noble in principle. People have to share your material under the same license, which means it will always remain openly licensed. A good thing, surely? &lt;b&gt;Not always&lt;/b&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a common use case for when it goes horribly wrong:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you upload a photo to Flickr, the default “open” license option is CC-BY-SA. This results in the vast majority of openly-licensed photos on Flickr being filed under this license. (The same applies, to an even greater extent, to Wikimedia content and the comparable GNU license). However, you cannot use CC-BY-SA licensed material under the &lt;b&gt;more open&lt;/b&gt; CC-BY license!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most users will probably be blissfully unaware of this unfortunate caveat. I suspect those unfamiliar with open licenses go “oh, this is cool” without realising that CC-BY-SA is actually a ‘closed’ license for those of us who work in the CC-BY or public domain arena.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The simple two-step solution: firstly, the default licensing-on-upload option on huge repos like Wikimedia and Flickr needs to change (to be more open!) and secondly users of such sites need to be better educated about their licensing options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We no longer live in a black and white world of closed vs. open. Open licensing has expanded to include many different flavours of openness. It’s just a pity that some of those flavours act on others in a ‘closed’ way.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/articles/why-cc-by-sa-should-die&quot;&gt;Why CC-BY-SA should die&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Nicola du Toit at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Nicola du Toit&lt;/a&gt; on March 28, 2013.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>

</feed>
